<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The evaporation of the apple of Palæstine: that is, The sifting of the answeres and rescripts, lately given, in the cause of the restitution of the Palatinate Together with a briefe demonstration of the nullities of the clandestine dispositions, by which, the electourship and the Palatinate hath beene transferred on the house of Bavaria. Translated out of Latine.</title>
            <title>Pomi Palaestini evaporatio. English</title>
            <author>Rusdorf, Johann Joachim von, 1589-1640.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 177 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 84 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01284</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11406</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102687</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838458</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838458</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2838</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01284)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2838)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1065:09)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The evaporation of the apple of Palæstine: that is, The sifting of the answeres and rescripts, lately given, in the cause of the restitution of the Palatinate Together with a briefe demonstration of the nullities of the clandestine dispositions, by which, the electourship and the Palatinate hath beene transferred on the house of Bavaria. Translated out of Latine.</title>
                  <title>Pomi Palaestini evaporatio. English</title>
                  <author>Rusdorf, Johann Joachim von, 1589-1640.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[160] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by A. G[riffin] for Ioyce Norton, and Richard Whitaker, and are to be sold at the Kings Armes in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XXXVII. [1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed "Volradus a Trubach", a misprint for the Latin edition's "Volradus a Frubach", i.e. Johann Joachim von Rusdorf.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: Pomi Palaestini evaporatio.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: pi²  [par.]⁴ A-S⁴ T² .</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The sifting of the imperiall answeres.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  History --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Holy Roman Empire --  History --  Ferdinand II, 1619-1637 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Holly Beeman</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:1"/>
            <p>THE EVAPORATION OF THE APPLE of Palaeſtine: That is, The Sifting of the Anſweres and Reſcripts, lately given, in the Cauſe of the Reſtitution of the Palatinate.</p>
            <p>Together With a briefe Demonſtration of the Nullities of the clandeſtine diſpoſitions, by which, the <hi>Electourſhip</hi> and the <hi>Palatinate</hi> hath beene transferred on the Houſe of <hi>Bavaria.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of Latine.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>A G.</hi> for <hi>Ioyce Norton,</hi> and <hi>Richard Whitaker,</hi> And are to be ſold at the Kings A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Pauls Church-yard.</hi> M.DC.XXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST HIGH and MIGHTIE PRINCE, Charles Lodowicke, Count Palatine of the Rhine, Archidapifer, and Prince Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour of the Sacred Empire, Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His, amongſt other reaſons (Moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious Prince) which prevailed with mee for the publication of this booke, was the prime and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall, that I might give notice to the whole world, and to them, who either
<pb facs="tcp:2838:3"/>
out of ignorance or affection, will not judge aright of the truth of things; that the cauſe, why that ſame ſolemne Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſage, which the moſt incomparable Peere, THOMAS HOVVARD, Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surry,</hi> lately performed in <hi>Germany,</hi> for the reſtitution of peace, and of the Palatinate, both, with one commiſſion to bee diſpatched, came not to a happy concluſion; was, neither in the moſt renowned King CHARLES, Your Vncle, nor in Your ſelfe: but in thoſe onely, who upon honeſt conditions and demands, would not ſuffer any thing that is moderate, and, of it ſelfe, equall and juſt, to bee obtained. For Your part, the mindes of all (that were any way intereſſed in You) were ready and wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to accept of any tolerable condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: But of the other ſide, ſuch things were preſcribed and exacted, as neither with honour and ſafety, nor with con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience and the good of the Common-wealth, could either bee granted or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted
<pb facs="tcp:2838:3"/>
unto: as it is evident by the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Acts, and which we have ſhewed in this Enodation.</p>
            <p>That which concerned mee in this buſineſſe, I hope, and that not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome diligence, I have diſcharged; that is to ſay, with our penne, ſtyle, writing, as much as our ability would permit, We doe vindicate, and maintaine both the juſtice of Your cauſe, and the innocency of Your perſon; and exhibite to the world, how great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice is done to Your ſelfe and Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred. It is Your duty now, ſince You have aſſaied all things <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> by faire meanes, and Your honeſt endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours have beene fruſtrated; that You ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of other remedies, and embrace ſuch inſtruments as, You may, by juſt armes, recover and wreſt from thoſe unjuſt uſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers and poſſeſſours that, which by violent force they have extorted from You. But that neither the power and fortune of Your adverſaries, nor the diffidence of Your
<pb facs="tcp:2838:4"/>
owne abilities, nor the warres proving for the moſt part unfortunate to King <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> Your Father, and his Allies, ſhould either deterre, procraſtinate, or make You timorous;
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Tu ne cede malis, ſed contrâ audentior ito.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>To evils doe not you give way,</l>
                  <l>But forward goe, with vertues ſway.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>The felicitie of Your adverſaries is ſo much the more ſlippery, by how much the higher it is aſcended: it is come to its height, and now ſtands tottering, by and by ready to fall with his branches, if but once ſhaken with ſome ſudden violence of the North &amp; South-wind. Things of moment are ruined in a moment, and the dubious fortune of that injurious and ingratefull Houſe, is wheeled about. It will not long re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine thoſe things which, by violence, fraud and injuſtice it hath detained from Thee.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quem Dies vidit veniens ſuperbum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hunc Dies vidit fugiens jacentem.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:2838:4"/>Whom the Sun riſing ſaw in honours place,</l>
               <l>Him the Sun ſetting ſaw in great diſgrace.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Goe forward then (moſt Illuſtrious Prince) bee bold, confident, adventure to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt: You ſhall have God, and the winds to ſecond your Sailes with a proſperous gale. A ſmall Army, guided with Councell and true valour, have many times ſubdued great forces. How often have a little Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, by marching forward and adventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring in warlike affaires, got the victory of a mighty hoſte?</p>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A Cane non magno ſaepe tenetur Aper.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Not ſeldome times, in open Field,</l>
                  <l>By little Dogge, great Boare is held.</l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>Even ſmall Creatures have procured danger and deſtruction to greateſt beaſts. Your cauſe is good, and You ſhall have Armes that will maintaine Your cauſe. The revenge of cruelty and injuſtice doth purſue your enemies: put on, perſiſt; if
<pb facs="tcp:2838:5"/>
that the Land denies a way, let the Sea prepare your paſſage to them: by perver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and preventing (ſaid that great King) by turning aſide, and by going forward are battailes wonne. The firſt preparations of warre are ſomewhat difficult; but, once gone into the field, You ſhall have Councels, Aſſociates, Companions, Souldiers. A ſmall Band, under the conduct of a couragious and valiant Leader, in time will encreaſe to a great Army. Obſerve the occaſions, and moments of times, actions, and men, as they offer themſelves, and thinke upon them. If You will aſſociate Your ſelfe with any of Your friends, that doe warre with You, You ſhall be a moſt welcome Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panion, and receive ſociable aſſiſtance from them. The experience of many ages, and the Annales doe teſtifie, that, in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning, all warres almoſt have gone a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them, to whom of right the victory appertained; but, in the end, the better cauſe have alwaies triumphed and prevailed. Fortune is not without its returne; ſhee
<pb facs="tcp:2838:5"/>
hath a long while favoured Your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries, and forſaken you: now the wheele is turned, ſhee may forſake them, and follow You. But whether am I carried? Theſe things are not for this place and time: Onely, the God of Heaven make and keepe You (moſt Illuſtrious Prince) flouriſhing and in ſafety, and proſper all Your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, and deſignes to Your hearts deſire. <hi>From the Vbij the Nones of March,</hi> 1637.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>VOLRADUS <hi>a</hi> TRUBACN.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:6"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:6"/>
            <head>To the Courteous Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S he who afarre off beholds Braſſe or Tinne, cannot eaſily diſtinguiſh the one from Silver, or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from Gold, unleſſe hee comes neere them; And as to one having the cryſtalline humors of his eyes darkened, or uſing ſpectacles, the object beheld, appeares leſſer, or greater, than in trueth it is: So, for the moſt part, thoſe, which are poſſeſſed with an over-weaning opinion and conceit, or led away by ignorance, or a falſe perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, or ſtirred up with a troublous paſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb facs="tcp:2838:7"/>
or ſudden motion of the mind, exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine things ſleightly, not prying into the more hidden ſecrets of the matter, and touching onely (as I may ſo ſpeake) the ſhell, but not at all attaining the kernell; they judge and determine farre otherwiſe, of mens actions, counſells, intentions, opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, words and writings, than is lawfull and agreeable to trueth.</p>
            <p>That fatall Palatine Cauſe, ſo generally knowne through the whole world, affords a notable and lively example hereof. <hi>Cui non dictus Hylas?</hi> Where is the man to whom this ſad newes hath not beene rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted? But who (I beſeech you) amongſt ſo many thouſands, doth at this preſent, ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and faithfully, and uprightly judge thereof? who among ſo many doth well know and underſtand it? For who, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to trueth and equity, without hatred or affection, doth rightly conceive, under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand and judge of the proſcription promul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated againſt King <hi>Fredericke</hi> the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour?
<pb facs="tcp:2838:7"/>
of intrenching upon, the taking a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, the alienation of the Electorall Palatine Dominions, and the Dignity and Offices thereunto annexed, and an entire, totall remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vall of theſe, unto the Bavarian Family? of the Ordainances made by the Emperor, the Bavarian and the reſt of their Confederates, of their pronounced Opinions, Decrees, Reſcripts, Conditions made knowne, agreed on, Covenants drawne, and the like? It is decreed in the Law, <hi>That every circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ought to be narrowly looked into, before the proceeding to ſentence:</hi> So alſo in things of ſo great conſequence, no ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence ought to be pronounced, untill all things be exactly weighed, aſwell for circumſtances and reaſons, quality of the times, conditions and intentions of men, and finally with a full underſtanding of words, ſentences and cauſes, things being examined by conſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and intreaty.</p>
            <p>If we ſhould deduce theſe things particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly, and one by one, as they ought to bee
<pb facs="tcp:2838:8"/>
weighed and diligently examined, it would require large volumes; we having reſerved the greater part of thoſe things untill another time, and for another labour and worke, which (by Gods aſsiſtance) wee ſhall ſhortly publiſh; for the preſent, we thought it worth the labour, to bring into the light, and expoſe to view, the intent and meaning of thoſe anſweres, reſcripts and decrees only, which the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the <hi>II.</hi> the laſt yere (in which the moſt Royall King <hi>Charles</hi> of great Britaine, ſent a ſolemne Embaſſage unto him, for gaining the reſtitution of the Palatinate, and of His Nephewes deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded from his onely Siſter the Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi>) had determined &amp; delivered: as alſo a briefe manifeſtation of injuſtice and the nullities, with which, thoſe alledged de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of the Emperour, concerning the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring and firme alienation of the Electorall dignitie, and revenues thereunto belonging granted to the Bavarians, doe (as it were) groane, and are ſtuffed; both becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:2838:8"/>
Wee were commanded and required there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, by them who had authority to doe it; as alſo, that they may give ſome light, or at leaſt open a gap, and prepare the way for thoſe my treatiſes which ſhall enſue: And to conclude, that out of theſe, ſome conjecture and gheſſe maybe had, what is to be thought of the other things performed in this matter in queſtion, by the adverſe part, either vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently or fraudulently practiſed. Perhaps ſome may ſay, that I ought to have beene more large and accurate concerning thoſe diſpoſitions, and in ſetting down the nullities of them. But I would have them know, that I would willingly have done that, and tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly have handled the particulars, if it might have beene lawfull to have taken a view of thoſe diſpoſitions, as they were firſt penned, the which (as it appeareth) never yet came to publike light, but alwayes were kept privately and in ſecret, as, at the firſt they were compoſed. And concerning the nullities of the urged pacification at Prague, whereby
<pb facs="tcp:2838:9"/>
it is pretended that thoſe diſpoſitions are ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified and confirmed, wee thought it a matter of incogitancie and indiſcretion, to make a long and tedious diſcourſe, not, becauſe wee deemed it not ſo much appertaining to Our purpoſe, as that, becauſe wee have found the ſame argument purpoſely handled by others, with exactneſſe of diligence, and no ſmall commendation. Should I alſo have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken to have made a ſtrict ſearch, and full diſcovery of the ſame matter, with my ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure pen, what other thing ſhould I have attempted, Than,
<q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Stellis nebulam ſpargere candidis?</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>— to over caſt the Heavens moſt bright,</l>
                  <l>With exhalat'ons that obſcure the light?</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>For Concluſion, Curteous Reader, I would intreat thee, to afford a favourable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation to theſe my extemporarie la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, for ſo you may give encouragement to
<pb facs="tcp:2838:9"/>
my endeavours, that I may with cheereful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe accompliſh (which) I yet forbeare) the Manifeſtation of things affected, and almoſt effected by the adverſaries, and expoſe them alſo ſpeedily to thy judgement and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding. Farewell heartily. From the Vbit the Nones of <hi>March. 1637.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:10"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2838:10"/>
            <head>THE SIFTING OF THE IMPERIALL Anſwers, given in the PALATINE Cauſe.</head>
            <head type="sub">With an annexed ſhort Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrance of the Nullities of the diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in the tranſlation of the Electorall Dignitie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He yeere laſt paſt, when the moſt Soveraign King of Great Britaine ſent his Ambaſſador, <hi>Thomas Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> Earle of <hi>Arundell</hi> and <hi>Surrie,</hi> Earle Marſhall of <hi>England,</hi> to the Emperour <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, to treat in the cauſe of the <hi>Prince Palatine</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire Reſtitution for his Nephew <hi>Prince Elector, Charles Lodowicke, and his Brethren,</hi> divers people ſcattered divers words, ſpent their judgements and opinions thereupon; the actions of Princes
<pb facs="tcp:2838:11"/>
(as it is cuſtomary) being diverſly conſtrued by the vulgar.</p>
            <p>Some averred, that the experience of ſo many yeeres, ſo many Ambaſſagies, ſo much interceeding already in the Cauſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, was a ſufficient teſtimony, of a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fault in that adviſe, by ſlackneſſe and haeſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; that nothing could bee expected by Treaty, nothing obtained by conference and reaſonable Conditions, nothing could bee extorted by the tranſactions of the mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and juſt King. That the Auſtrians, Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian, and their Confederates, having alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy deſtinated the Line of the Prince Palatine for death, would never grant that it ſhould riſe againe, and the exiled Palatine Princes more carefull of the ancient liberty and greater enemies to innovation then the reſt, now growne ſtronger, by a new alliance and friendſhip of forraigne Kings, being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their former eſtate, ſhould returne into their Country, and be a terrour to thoſe families, and like thornes in their eyes. That the Auſtrians, being growne more inſolent
<pb facs="tcp:2838:11"/>
by the timorouſneſſe of the adverſe Partie, had already ſetled to their owne affaires. That the Palatine buſineſſe did more and more decline, that the Prince his friends, Companions and Aſſiſtants, ſuſpended with feare and doubt, and often deluded with hope of taking Armes in the Cauſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, were compelled by neceſſity to leave his Partie, and enter into new Confoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deracies. That the Swedes and the French onely were yet remaining, whoſe love and alliance was to be accepted, with whom He ſhould joyne in Armes, and Counſell, till with a potent and victorious Army, they might weary the Auſtrians. That the occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was not to be neglected, that this Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie was to be ſhaken off; that to attempt the negotiation againe by Treaties, (which ſo often had prooved fruitleſſe) and to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare Armes, in which the onely hope of attaining the end conſiſted, was a token of indiſcretion or ſluggiſhneſſe. Have not the Kings of England by the ſpace of theſe 18. yeeres bin deluded by the Auſtrians? will
<pb facs="tcp:2838:12"/>
they ſtill ſuffer themſelves to be gulled with words? Dare they not awake from ſleepe, and remember their former injuries? Theſe, and words to the ſame effect, were ſpoken commonly by the military men, which breathed out warre, and burned with a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire thereunto.</p>
            <p>Others, which would be accounted more moderate, and of a more peaceable conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, commended the Kings Wiſedome, Piety, and equanimity, granting notwithſtanding, that nothing hath bin done hitherto by ſo many Legations and Embaſſies in the Cauſe of the Palatinate, but that all that labour and endeavour vaniſhed into ſmoke: Yet that it was to be conſidered; That after the death of the King <hi>Friderick,</hi> for whom eſpecially it was interceded, whoſe reſtitution, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation was chiefly aimed at; whom the Caeſareans ſtiled the Author, and fire-brand of all thoſe troubles, and with whom only they averred themſelves to be offended. The ſtate of things was not a little altered, and therefore it was probable, that their ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred
<pb facs="tcp:2838:12"/>
and wrath was ſomewhat abated, that the Imperialiſts (as they pretended) would now become more moderate men, and ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting off their old rancour, the father being dead, would not take vengeance of the guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe children, and therefore concluded the King did wiſely, that by a ſolemne Legation in the name of his Nephews, He attempted to make their compoſition, and procure the reſtitution upon Conditions, and might try whether their adverſaries were ſtill as cruell and inſolent againſt them, as they had bin formerly againſt their father, ſeeing there was far leſſe cauſe for it, againſt them, then againſt him.</p>
            <p>Beſides, of the other ſide, the King had good hope to obtaine their reſtitution, that he was deſired to come to a Parley, and to ſend an Embaſſie with full power to Caeſar, aſſoone as might be; and theſe concurrents promiſed an happy iſſue. This hope if hee had deſpiſed, or either relinquiſhed the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as loſt, or made warre upon that occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, the adverſaries then, might have had
<pb facs="tcp:2838:13"/>
good cauſe, and pretence, to complaine of his weakeneſſe or raſhneſſe.</p>
            <p>Beſides, they ſaid, there were ſome other cauſes that made the King demurre upon the matter, holding it unfit to take Armes with vnwaſhed hands, and before hee had better ſetled his owne affaires; and that though it was to be feared, that this Embaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie would be alſo fruitleſſe, and unhappy, and in the meane ſeaſon the faire occaſion of warre would be neglected; Yet the King nevertheleſſe, ſhould thereby get this bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit; that not onely the juſtice of the cauſe, the innocency of his Nephewes, the pride of their enemies, and the injuries done by them, would more cleerely appeare; but that him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe alſo muſt be juſtly excuſed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended, if after all experiments, and this laſt endeavour (which yet remained) of making a Peace by Treaties, he ſhould bee unwillingly forced to attempt another way.</p>
            <p>Theſe, and the like reaſons, mooved the deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vedly ſtiled, moſt Wiſe and Moderate King, to ſend His Ambaſſador <hi>Thomas Howard</hi> Earle of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rundel</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:13"/>
and <hi>Sarri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> with all ſpeed to Caeſar, with perfect inſtructions for that negotiation. At the Ambaſſadors firſt arrivall in <hi>Germany,</hi> ſome things happened beyond his expectation; from whence, the more curious ſort of men, began to divine forthwith of the ſucceſſe of his Embaſſie.</p>
            <p>For, firſt, he was compelled to bee an eye-wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the cruelties, practiſed upon the bodies, and goods, of the miſerable Citizens, and inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of <hi>Frankendale,</hi> for whom himſelfe became an interceſſor. Some were clapt in priſon, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained by threats, and famine, to pay their unjuſt ranſomes: others vexed with extorſions, tributes, burthens, and ſervices, pined away for ſorrow: the more he complained, and intreated for them, the ſharper was their vſage; No mercy could hee obtaine for them, by his ſuit and intreaties either from Caeſar, the King of <hi>Hungary</hi> their Miniſters, or the Spaniſh Ambaſſadors: no aſſurance that thoſe Conditions which were granted them at their yeelding ſhould be obſerved; but from the time that he firſt pleaded for them, they were (as on purpoſe) uſed more hardly. And how then could he hope to obtaine the maine ſuit, when theſe trifles were denyed him.</p>
            <p>Againe, when at <hi>Norimberg,</hi> he underſtood by <hi>Iohn Taylor,</hi> who came from the Emperors Court, that the King of <hi>Hungary,</hi> (who was then at <hi>Nord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingen,</hi> in <hi>Swaben,</hi> and going to the Imperiall Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my) deſired, that he would meet him upon the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:14"/>
way, (as he ſeemed deſirous to ſpeake with the Ambaſſador) he ſent <hi>Taylor</hi> before him, to appoint the time, and the place of their meeting, and to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme him of what was done. But after ſome dayes waiting for an anſwere, he perceived in the end, the King did either ſeeme leſſe carefull of meeting him, then any other buſineſſe, or elſe to have meerely forgot it; And yet more, neither by Letters nor Agent (which is the cuſtome, when the Ambaſſadors of Kings come to the Provinces, and Dominions of other Princes) did hee vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafe to greet him; which was accounted, a token, either of pride, or contempt, or inurbanity.</p>
            <p>At laſt, he found the King according to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers command and the writings drawen up at <hi>Donawerth,</hi> (the very ſame time when they had ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to meet) giving, and delivering to the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, certaine conſecrated goods, lands, revenues, and intire Monaſteries, in the Lower Palatinate; which upon the marriage of the Queene of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mia</hi> his Kings ſiſter, were conveighed unto her for her Iointure, which was no good token, of a will inclining to reſtitution, when he ſhewed himſelfe more forward, to alienate, rend, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtract that eſtate, then to reſtore it.</p>
            <p>When he came to <hi>Lintz</hi> (a towne of eminency in the upper Auſtria) where Caeſar then abode, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within few dayes after bound for <hi>Ratisbon,</hi> where the Septemvirat Counſell was aſſembled; he was indeed entertained in great ſtate, and much
<pb facs="tcp:2838:14"/>
complement, and had free and frequent acceſſe to Caeſar and the Empreſſe; but about the Cauſe he came to treat of, for many dayes, he found a ſtill ſilence. Nevertheleſſe, at laſt impatient of delay, he having more importunately urged it, Caeſar, as ſeeming deſirous to treat of the buſineſſe ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, appointed certain Counſellors, who ſhould conferre with him; namely, the Biſhop of <hi>Vienna, Peter Henry Stralendorff</hi> Vice-Chancellor of the Empire, and <hi>Iuſtus Gebhard</hi> a Civilian. Once they met, and no more, to wit, upon the 14. of the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lends of <hi>Auguſt:</hi> for the Ambaſſador having peru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Commiſſion which the Emperour had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven his Counſellours, for treating about this buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, found amongſt other inſtructions, this, That the King of Great Britaine, by <hi>Iohn Taylor,</hi> had offered to enter into, and ſettle an offenſive, and defenſive League, with his Imperiall Majeſty and the houſe of Auſtria, againſt the common ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies and adverſaries of that State.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſadour knowing this to be falſe, and againſt the Kings repute, credit, and integrity; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted that by vertue of his office, he was bound to vindicate the King, from this imputation, and to confute, and contradict it both by word and writing; And this was the cauſe which then hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him from further diſcourſe with them; And thus he began;</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:15"/>Theſe things (ſaid he) being ſo unworthy, and altogether from the meaning, faith, and integrity of the Kings Majeſty, I have con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, that it wholly appertaineth to my office, and the honour and dignity of his Royall Majeſty, to declare the ſorrow, and griefe of mind which I have hence recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, both by word and writing, to your Imperiall Majeſty; prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting publikely; That, it is not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly againſt the intention of my So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraigne the King, nor can it bee ſpoken without ſome note of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minie, that He hath of his owne ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord offered an offenſive and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſive Leagve, to your Imperiall Majeſty, and the whole houſe of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:15"/>
Auſtria, againſt the enemies of that family: which truely would tend both to the offence of the reſt of His Majeſties Confederates, who might thence take juſt occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſuſpition, and complaint, and might alſo oblige His Majeſty to what He cannot doe, with His honour and conſcience, without great cauſe given by His Allies, to relinquiſh their neceſsitude, and ſo involve himſelfe in a perpetuall neceſsity of warre.</p>
            <p>But, if <hi>Iohn Taylor</hi> the Agent for the King, my Soveraigne, hath promiſed any ſuch thing, or mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred any hopes of it, as it is expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſet downe, in the words of that Commiſsion: I muſt needs ſpeake
<pb facs="tcp:2838:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:16"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:17"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:18"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:19"/>
it, he hath done it without autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, and is bound to give an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, for that action. But if he be free from that imputation, (as he proteſteth he is, affirming that he never ſpake ſuch words, appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling withall to his remembrances, delivered to the Imperiall Court,) what can I elſe inferre, or ſay, But that there is a ſtrange affront, done both to the King, and me His Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, when to my face, by a publike eſcript ſuch diſhonoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and ſtrange things, are thruſt upon us?</p>
            <p>The caſe then being thus; I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech your Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, that your wiſedome would weigh, and ſo order this matter
<pb facs="tcp:2838:19"/>
that no ſuch thing, as may be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minous and diſhonourable to the King, or my ſelfe, may bee done, written, or ſpoke: but that all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laies and circumſtances ſet apart, wee may come ſincerely to the matter, and, as ſoone as may bee, I may receive that anſwer which may be welcome, acceptable, and ſatisfactory to his Royall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, and may alſo bee a token that the buſineſſe is handled ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, and with hope of good ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Caeſar</hi> replyed hereunto, by a large writing, and full of words, both explaining his owne minde and opinion, and repeating out of the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brances what ever at any time had beene done, ſayd, written, and treated to, and fro, concerning the matter, and forme of the propounded league. And in the end concluded thus.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:20"/>All theſe things then being thus, as they are proved out of the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall writings, which are alledged and may be ſeene; and ſeeing that by them, it may eaſily appeare to any one, that neither his Sacred Imperiall Majeſty, nor the moſt Illuſtrious King of great Britaine, had any intention to conclude an offenſive and defenſive League of one ſide onely, and onely againſt the enemies of one of them, but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the common adverſaries of both Parties; ſeeing alſo, that if the concluſion had beene made onely againſt the enemies of one Party, it had beene repugnant to the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of ſuch Confederacies; and ſince otherwiſe the limitation and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:20"/>
moderation of ſuch agreements ought to depend upon the treaties uſed in their confirmation; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by is diſcovered what is agreeing to reaſon, and honourable, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeming both Parties. And to conclude, when it cannot bee thought, that the equity, and good affection of his Sacred and Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Majeſty, towards the Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King of Great Britaine, would deſire any thing of him, that ſhould be contrary to his reputa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and dignity: His Imperiall Majeſty doth confidently beleeve, that there is no man who will blame Him, that Hee would thus queſtion this matter, and with all gentleneſſe, explaine it; not deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2838:21"/>
nevertheleſſe, but that there may be ſuch moderation uſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the often me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tioned clauſe, as by a common conſent may bee thought fit, to take away all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of offence.</p>
            <p>But for the principall matter, he wrote againe to this effect,</p>
            <p>That he remembred he had de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared himſelfe to the Agent of the ſaid moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Britaine, in what ſenſe, he deſired that to ſundry his former decrees, and namely that of the xxiv. of <hi>February</hi> laſt paſt, there might bee added a new Condition, to wit, in reſpect of the cauſes and reaſons there alledged; that if the Count Palatine <hi>Charles Lodowick,</hi> ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:2838:21"/>
perform the conditions contained in the ſaid decree, then hee would mercifully diſcharge Him of the Imperiall Ban, derived unto Him by his fathers treſpaſſe, that he might bee received into the ſtate &amp; degree of the Princes of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Empire, and hee would alſo reſtore him, into no deſpicable part of his ancient dominions; and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the agreement ſetle him in the ſame. Laſtly, when there ſhould bee a treaty thereon; hee would obſerve ſuch moderation, both concerning the Electorall Dignity, and other things then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, and propounded, that in thoſe things, which might be granted upon tearmes of juſtice,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:22"/>
both the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Brittaine, might ſee the good affection of his Sacred Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty towards him, and alſo the often named Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, might eaſily apprehend the readineſſe of his favour towards him. That his Sacred Imperiall Majeſty, doth yet the more firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly continue the ſame gracious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and ſtand to the ſaid de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, the rather, becauſe by the ſaid Lord Ambaſſadour, and former Letters, and Commiſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, hee hath beene certified, of the good affection of the moſt Illuſtrious mentioned King, (who had no other than a faire and ſincere intention, in all for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer
<pb facs="tcp:2838:22"/>
treaties, and propoſitions to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards himſelfe and his Princely family:) to which will, and inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, his Sacred Imperiall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty affirmeth he will be anſwera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and ſo remaine conſtantly, judging it fit, that the matter of which he had beene pleaſed, once to have made a Treaty, ſhould now alſo remaine eſtabliſhed. And yet moreover, ſeeing his often na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Sacred Imperiall Majeſty, not bound by any Law, but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved thereunto by his meere Grace and Imperiall mercy, and eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally by his affection and love to the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Britaine, and the deſired ſight of their hereafter mutuall Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racy,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:23"/>
hath already thus farre de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared, and doth yet declare Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: And alſo, the forenamed Lord Ambaſſadour having ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned himſelfe, to this purpoſe, that it is not the intention, of his moſt Soveraigne King, that the foreſaid totall reſtitution, ſhould be made inſtantly; hence, his Sacred Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty thought it fit, and belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, it would enſue, that the ſaid Lord Ambaſſadour, would not be unwilling to explaine himſelfe any further, than concerning the manner, of the deſired totall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution, and eſpecially touching the Electorall dignity, as alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout thoſe things, of which ſome hope was given to his ſaid
<pb facs="tcp:2838:23"/>
Sacred Imperiall Majeſty; to wit, how farre the ſaid King of great Brittaine, would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage Himſelfe with his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, and his whole Princely Houſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, and what hee would, and might doe for their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit.</p>
            <p>To this the Ambaſſadour anſwered, That, it appeared plainely, out of his owne Imperiall anſwere, that neither any of the Kings ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, nor the King him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, in any of his writings, had made mention of ſuch a league, no not ſo much as by word, or familiar diſcourſe, unleſſe ſome ſuch thing, might bee
<pb facs="tcp:2838:24"/>
inferred, to have beene ſpoken out of the bare Relation of the Count of Schonburg, the Imperiall Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador in Spaine; which never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe, doth not in all things a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with the (pretended) offered co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>federacy. And if any ſuch thing ſhould have happened in their private conference, yet it is a new and unheard of way of Treaty; that all things which in a familiar diſcourſe, are propounded by pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like miniſters, ſhould be inſerted into publike inſtruments under the Seale, and afterwards objected againſt them. But yet, what ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of Confederacy, and under what Conditions it was offered, by His Royall Majeſty, it did
<pb facs="tcp:2838:24"/>
plainely appeare, both by the words and meaning of the wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and ſpeakers; to wit, that, If his Imperiall Majeſty, regarding the interceſsion of His Royall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, ſhould reſtore the Electorall Palatinate, with the annexed dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and liberties, and by this meanes lay the foundation of a ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſetled Peace in the Empire; then His Royall Majeſty, would enter into a Covenant with His Imperiall Majeſty, and the Fam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Houſe of Auſtria, and with the Septemvirate and States of the Empire, for the obtaining of the Peace and generall tranquility, and the ſetling of it upon equall Conditions on both ſides; and to
<pb facs="tcp:2838:25"/>
defend it againſt all thoſe, who ſhould dare to impugne ſuch a ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred agreement. Wherefore, he did humbly beſeech His Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Majeſty, that no ſuch preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded League, might any more bee objected to the moſt Illuſtrious King, his moſt gracious Lord, or him His Ambaſſadour; nor might it bee any more an hinderance, whereby the forementioned ple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary reſtitution, might not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turely be perfected, without fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther procraſtination.</p>
            <p>Next he refuteth, and oppoſeth the propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and offer made by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> in ſtanding to his own Decree, or Declaration given to <hi>Iohn Taylor, Febr.</hi> 24. <hi>Anno</hi> 1636. ſaying;</p>
            <p>That he in his propoſition, and firſt bill of remembrance, had
<pb facs="tcp:2838:25"/>
plainely ſhewed, that the declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was of ſuch condition, as could give the King no ſatisfaction, both becauſe the things therein offered, were far inferiour to His hope and expectation; in that the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of the moſt Illuſtrious Prince, the Electour, His Nephew was included and circumſcribed within the narrow compaſſe of ſome one part of His Dominion (which nevertheleſſe is not yet named) as alſo, becauſe it is ſaid, that his Imperiall Majeſty would acquit the Count Palatine <hi>Charles Lodowick</hi> of the Imperial Ban deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved unto him by reaſon of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers treſpaſſe, to the end he might bee received againe amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:2838:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:26"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:27"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:28"/>
the Princes of the Empire, if He ſhould fulfill the Conditions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein: When notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, it is manifeſt, that the moſt Illuſtrious Electour, <hi>Charles Lodowick,</hi> is guiltleſſe, and free from all offence, and born a Prince of the Empire; that the right gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by God, by nature, and the law, appertaines unto Him, and cannot bee taken from Him, as might be ſhewen more largely, if need required. Moreover, as the moſt Illuſtious King deſires, thankfully to entertaine the grace and clemency of His Imperiall Majeſty; ſo it would be altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unjuſt, and reproachfull both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o Himſelfe, and His Nephews,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:28"/>
to forſake the equity and juſtice of the cauſe; which is grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the law of Nature and Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, the Golden and other Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Bulls, and the fundamentall Lawes of the Empire, as moſt plainely may be proved in its pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per time and place.</p>
            <p>As concerning the manner of the deſired reſtitution, He know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth no other, than that the moſt Illuſtrious Elector <hi>Charles Lodowick</hi> and his Brethren, by an Imperiall decree, reall entrance, and ſolemne Inveſtiture (cuſtomary in caſes of this nature) be ſpeedily reſtored unto their ancient Dignities, Fees, Poſſeſsions and Priviledges: Then that they againe ſhould promiſe
<pb facs="tcp:2838:29"/>
reciprocally, and doe really, what ſuch homagers and Princes of the Empire, inveſted, and admitted into poſſeſsion, are bound and ought to doe and performe, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the right, cuſtome, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Empire. But in the behalfe of his moſt Soveraigne King, he doth undertake, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that, if for His ſake, this reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution be haſtned, and done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out delay; then His royall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, ſhould willingly performe thoſe things which may plainely teſtifie, His royall, and ſingular in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination towards his Imperiall Majeſty, the famous houſe of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria, and peace of Germany, and that He ſhould ſeale to all this, and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:29"/>
confirme it, both in His owne name, and the name of His Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews, in publike writings, and conditions; to which end, he hath already ſent his Ambaſſador, with a ſufficient commiſſion, and ample power, to his Imperiall Majeſty, and the Princes of the Empire.</p>
            <p>To this the Emperour replyed firſt by writing, and afterward by his Counſellors, <hi>viva voce;</hi> by writing in theſe words:</p>
            <p>That for the preſent, He held it needleſſe to diſpute of priviledges; that, the authority of the Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Majeſty, is undoubtedly grounded not onely upon the common Lawes, but the peculi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar conſtitutions of the Empire, and the Decrees of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bull, and confirmed by
<pb facs="tcp:2838:30"/>
very many, both ancient, and late preſidents. That His Imperiall Majeſty, had uſed this liberty, for the free diſpoſing of the Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and Dignities of the often na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Palatine, which diſpoſals are ſince confirmed by the late Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at Prague, and conſequently, by all the Princes of the Sacred Roman Empire. From hence, if things he well ſcanned it may ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily appeare, whether there be any and of what value that amity is, which his Imperiall Majeſty hath formerly offred, and doth yet of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer, to the children of the Count Palatine, and how much it ought to be eſteemed.</p>
            <p>All which being truth, and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:2838:30"/>
that his mentioned Imperiall Majeſty, hath declared himſelfe both in reſpect of his affection, and inclination toward the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine; as alſo in reſpect of his cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency, toward His Nephewes, ſometimes the children of <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke</hi> Palatine, according to the manner, and under the conditions contained, in the often mentioned decree of the 24<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of February: Therefore, hee thinkes it fit, and doth in all curteſie require it, that the ſaid Lord Ambaſſadour (if it ſtand with his liking) would come to particulars, and more plainely either by writing, or (if it pleaſe him) which his Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb facs="tcp:2838:31"/>
Majeſty thinkes more conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient) by conferring with his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſties Commiſsioners, to explaine what the moſt Illuſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous King of Great Britaine would offer reciprocally, and intends to performe to his Imperiall Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, for theſe like proffers; that ſo, as the cuſtome is, in a faire equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>page, it may be treated, agreed, and concluded, of things required and to be done on both parties.</p>
            <p>The Ambaſſador having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved this anſwere, declared himſelfe to be therewith nothing ſatisfied; and therefore deſired, that his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty would expreſſe his minde more plainely and fully; and determinately and abſolutely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare
<pb facs="tcp:2838:31"/>
whether he had reſolved to do any thing in this caſe, and what; and upon what Conditions hee would reſtore in particular.</p>
            <p>He therefore having called his Counſell, upon the Kalends of <hi>September,</hi> commanded them to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire to the Ambaſſadour, and ſpeake unto him to this effect;</p>
            <p>That His Imperiall Majeſty, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving weighed and conſidered all things, which aſwell hitherto had been preſented by the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour, as alſo were neceſſarily conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable in this caſe, he would faire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſincerely, deliver his mind in this manner.</p>
            <p>That the whole negotiation, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted eſpecially upon three heads; The firſt is, for reſtitution of the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:32"/>
Lower Palatinate; but it muſt bee knowne, that the King of Spaine, hold one part thereof, as a pledge for his great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence, in the execution com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to his truſt; that the Bavarian hold the other part, upon the like tearmes; and now it was agreeable to rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon and juſtice, that both theſe perſonages ſhould receive ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, before that they reſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their pledges, and gages: that His Imperiall Majeſty had dealt diligently with them both, and ſo farre prevailed with them, that they had conſented to the Reſtitution, but yet upon this condition, that ſome profits and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:32"/>
emoluments might bee firſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured, and performed to them, in right of compenſation. And that the Count Palatine, might ſafely, quietly, and without impeachment, enjoy the things to bee reſtored; His Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Majeſty, of His meere fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, would abrogate His proſcription, and receive Him into the State, and Degree of the Princes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire.</p>
            <p>The ſecond head concerneth the Electorall dignity. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe His Imperiall Majeſty, hath lately, freely, and abſolutely diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed thereof, as a thing divol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to His Majeſty and the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:33"/>
Empire the Electours conſenting and approoving the Act, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the preſcript of the Lawes, and Imperiall Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, and had transferred it upon the Duke of Bavaria (a man of high deſervings with Caeſar, and the whole Empire,) and to the Line of <hi>William,</hi> both by Inveſtiture and other Obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations; ſo that the buſineſſe is now eſtabliſhed, confirmed, and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable, nor is it lawfull to Treat of the reſtoring thereof, ſo long as any man of that Line ſhall be ſurviving.</p>
            <p>The third head concernes the Vpper Palatinate. And of this it muſt bee concluded, as of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:33"/>
the Electorall Dignity; for thoſe territories, and dominions were already delivered up to the Duke of Bavaria, in part of payment of the expences, which that Duke had beene at, in the Emperours behalfe, for the recovery of Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia. And now things being in this ſtate, and His Imperi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Majeſty, having thus ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerely, and plainely, diſclo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his minde; it is very requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that the Anbaſſadour alſo ſhould now declare what the King againe will doe, for the behoofe and benefit of his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, in reſpect of his Imperiall grace, and good affection, and what manner of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:34"/>
league, he intendeth to make with him.</p>
            <p>To this the Ammbaſſadour anſwered in few words:</p>
            <p>That hee returned thankes to <hi>Caeſar,</hi> that Hee would ſo clearely explaine His meaning; for now it was ſufficiently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent, what the King (who did little expect this anſwere) might, and ought to hope for in this whole negotiation; but yet, hee ſhould have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned him more thankes, if this anſwere had come ſooner, and preſently upon his arrivall at the Imperiall Court, or rather, before hee had come
<pb facs="tcp:2838:34"/>
out of England, for then peradventure, there might have beene a ſparing of time, and charge, and there ſhould have beene no need of ſo full a Comiſsion, and ſolemne Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation. That now his mouth was ſtopped, that hee might neither goe further, nor make any larger declaration, that now there was nothing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining for him to doe, but to certifie his King of all the proceedings, which hee would doe faithfully, and without affection; <hi>Caeſar</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving liberty to doe the ſame by his owne ſervants, if perhaps, hee did ſuſpect
<pb facs="tcp:2838:35"/>
that hee would adde to the truth, or diminiſh from it, by his rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>Two daies after, hee ſpake with <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe, repeating the meſſage delivered unto him by his Agents, and his owne anſwer, and that according to his duty, hee would enforme the King of all paſſages, by a ſpeedy Poſt. His letters he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patcheth to the King in England, feigning in the meane ſeaſon that he would not ſtay to expect the returne of the Meſſenger: thinking, that the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration for his departure would move and incline the Caeſareans (who perhaps were unwilling that hee ſhould depart the buſineſſe undone, and the foile of the treaty broken off) to moderation and more reaſonable termes: But all was in vaine, time ſlipt away, and the Poſt in the meane while returned, bringing letters from the King to the Ambaſſadour, by which he was comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that ſeeing there was no hope of obtaining the reſtitution of the Electorall Palatinate upon indifferent tearmes; to returne home, and leave <hi>Iohn Taylor</hi> in the Caeſarean Court. When the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perialiſts ſaw the Ambaſſadour ready to depart, they uſed all meanes of induſtry and art, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine him longer. And to this end the King of Hungary, the ſonne of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> who was newly come to the Dyet, ſtayed the Embaſſadours purpoſe of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:35"/>
departing, by giving ſpeciall hope, that he would procure, that the treatiſe of reſtitution, ſhould be brought to an happy iſſue, and the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour ſhould have no cauſe of complaint or repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, if he attended upon it a while longer. The Ambaſſadour therefore thought it a point of diſcretion, to deferre his departure for ſome daies; as well, that hee might try whether <hi>Caeſar</hi> would deliver any tearmes more indifferent and moderate; as alſo, that hee might not bee juſtly charged, that hee was too haſty, and refuſed to heare thoſe things which to bee openly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded would be offered: But when the time was ſtill delayed, the matter being tranſmitted to the adviſe of the Electours, whoſe opinions (as it was given out) muſt firſt bee knowne, the Ambaſſadour having twice or thrice called upon them for their reſolutions, and ſeeing himſelfe to attend in vaine, went to the Electours, the King and <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and bad them farewell, the 6<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the ides of November.</p>
            <p>At his departure, a new promiſe and hope was given him, that before his going out of Germany, letters ſhould be tranſmitted to him, containing ſuch an anſwere, as ſhould come neerer to his demands. At Noreimberg indeed hee received ſome letters, and amongſt them, one to the Queene <hi>Elizabeth;</hi> but upon the ſuperſcription, there was purpoſely omitted the title of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctreſſe, and Princeſſe Palatine, under a falſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:36"/>
that this title is not to be given Her by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the offence of Her proſcribed husband. The Ambaſſadour therefore with indignation, and words of anger, ſent backe thoſe letters thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther from whence they came. And ſurely, it is a matter of cruelty and injuſtice unheard of, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver knowne amongſt Barbarians, never practiſed in thoſe bloody proſcriptions of <hi>Sylla</hi> and <hi>Marius,</hi> nor under the Triumvirat, that an innocent wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, for the crime of her husband, (how hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous and apparent ſoever) ſhould be deprived of the priviledges, goods dignities, and titles, which ſhe had, and enjoyed before the offence done; according to the dayly practice (ſo it is preſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med) of the Caeſareans, againſt the Queene of Bohemia, whoſe dowry is not onely taken from her, by force and injury, but they attempt alſo to deprive Her of her name, title, and dignity, which She had by marriage; when nevertheleſſe on the contrary part, it is alleaged, that her huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band was never convicted of the crime laid to His charge: and yet, unheard by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> (in his owne cauſe) undefended, not called, Hee is unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, unjuſtly, and for no cauſe, but hatred, and deſire of revenge, proſcribed. But to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>For a long time, there was no newes of the anſwere promiſed to the Engliſh Ambaſſadour. At laſt a paper drawne up the 14<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lends of February, (a declaration or notification,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:36"/>
ye may call it either) was ſent over into England; to this effect.</p>
            <p>That his Imperiall Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, as ſoone as Hee knew the chiefeſt difficulty which hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered this negotiation, from the deſired effect of their more neere alliance, and confedera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, depended on this, that the moſt Illuſtrious King deſired ſome more ample ſatisfaction, concerning his Nephew in point of the Electorall digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, had not intermitted, with much care to ſeeke, and finde out all thoſe meanes, which were requiſite for the paſsing of that difficulty, by conferring of that buſineſſe both with the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:37"/>
Illuſtrious Electoral Colledge, and with them, who were more particularly intreſſed therein, and without whoſe conſent (His affaires being as they are) it ſtood not with the integrity of His Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty, to conclude. When there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, ſome meanes were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered, which gave ſome hope that the foreſaid difficulty concerning the Electorall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity (though the Line of <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am</hi> ſometime Duke of Bavaria was ſtill remaining) might be over paſſed, and ſome more ample ſatisfaction given to the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Brittaine, his Romane royall
<pb facs="tcp:2838:37"/>
Majeſty would omit no time to ſignifie ſo much to <hi>Iohn Taylor,</hi> Agent in that nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiation, for the King of Great Brittaine, and leſt there to that purpoſe, who ſhould acquaint his King therewit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> as ſoone as might be, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> knew how to provide, that a ſufficient Commiſsion, to retreate, and conclude this buſineſſe of reſtitution, and confederation, might be tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to him with all ſpeed, or given to ſome other, who ſhould bee ſent over for that diſpatch.</p>
            <p>And this is a briefe and compendiary Relation of thoſe things which have beene done, ſpoken,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:38"/>
and written on both ſides in this ſolemne Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie. But now for the eaſier underſtanding of the conſequents, it is firſt to be obſerved; That the Engliſh Ambaſſadour, in the beginning of his Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, in the firſt propoſition, and againe in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther declaration to the Emperour, made an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion againſt that Decree of <hi>Caeſar</hi> (as they call it) of the 24. day of <hi>February,</hi> both by rejecting it, as a nullity, and frivolous; as alſo by ſhewing that the Conditions therein preſcribed, were, far beneath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hope and expectation, which the moſt Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>us King of England conceived, of the intire reſtitution of the Palatinate; that is, as well of the Territories, as the Electorall Office; and therefore might give juſt cauſe of doubt, and diffidence of ſucceſſe in the buſineſſe, and of ſuperſeding his endeavour by diſpatch of his Legation, unleſſe that otherwiſe (and that by <hi>Taylor</hi> himſelfe, to whom that decree was delivered) a more ample, better ſeaſoned, and firmer hope and caution were given in the name of his Imperiall Majeſty, of a firme and full ſatisfaction and gratification, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the reſtitution of the Palatinate.</p>
            <p>And ſurely it is not to be queſtioned, that the moſt wiſe and mighty King, would ever have ſent His Ambaſſadour, for ſuch jeiune and frothy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions; ſo full of diſhonour and prejudice, as were contained in that writing; for unleſſe He had a better and more certaine foundation of His hope, and beene induced by other arguments and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:38"/>
perſwaſions, he would have ſpared His expence in ſo honourable a Legation.</p>
            <p>Beſides; it is to be conſidered, that the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour in his firſt anſwere which he gave the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour at <hi>Lintz,</hi> the 30. day of <hi>Iune</hi> did ſilently acknowledge; that, that hope proceeded from himſelfe; becauſe, that then he neither contradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted it, nor excepted againſt it; and further, by his ſilence allowed that exception which the Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſadour, the 18 of <hi>Iune,</hi> had propounded againſt the ſaid Decree of the 24. of <hi>February,</hi> and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged it to be grounded upon trueth and reaſon. But afterward, when he ſo confidently contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted it, adding withall that He wondred upon what ground the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour ſuppoſed, that he ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred hope either of more ample grace or fuller reſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, than what was contained in the often remembred Decree; It was a ſigne that hee reſolved not to vary from his firſt determination, whatſoever any others might ſay, or beleeve to the contrary.</p>
            <p>And now it is worthy your labour to conſider, and enquire what, and of what quality, thoſe of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers made by <hi>Caeſar</hi> were, which are ſo often repea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:39"/>
and are commanded to be eſteemed at ſo high a rate, and to be reputed, for a ſingular kindneſſe, and then under what conditions, they were to bee exhibited, and of what qualitie thoſe things are, which are againe required to bee performed, by the King, and <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> the Electour, in acknowledgement of ſo great a favour.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Emperour offers to abſolve <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> from the Imperiall outlawrie, which is derived upon him for his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers offence, to that end and purpoſe, that he may be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to the ſtate and degree of a Prince of the ſacred Romane Empire: A goodly favour (queſtionleſſe) for him, who is a Prince borne, and by the law of the Empire, his owne priviledge and right of Primo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geniture, an Electour; that not by his fathers favor, and the way of inheritance, but proviſion of the Law, and Covenant of the firſt Atchievour, and by the priviledge of his family doth ſucceed into the Electorate: If hee accept this offer of Caeſars, in that ſenſe it is profered, hee is forced to acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and confeſſe firſt; that the over haſtened
<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:39"/>
Ban againſt his father, was lawfull and juſt, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated according to Law. Secondly, that the ſame proſcription ſtandeth alſo in force againſt him, no otherwiſe than if hee himſelfe had beene proclaimed a proſcribed perſon, and had neede of pardon. Either of which he could not doe, but with prejudice to his moſt manifeſt right, and by bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding both his bleſſed father, himſelfe, and his, with a note of ignominy: Nor could he do it with a good conſcience, or without the crime of greateſt ingra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; both becauſe, he ſhould wound the honour and eſtimation of his father, whileſt by his ſilence hee ſhould in a manner acknowledge and confeſſe him to have been a rebell, enemy, and traytour to his Imperiall Majeſtie, and therefore lawfully pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed; as alſo becauſe he is perſwaded in his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that his father is wronged and the Ban de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced againſt him, is unlawfull and of no vali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditie; and if it had been decreed, and pronounced legally, yet it cannot reach his owne perſon, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing innocent, and was borne long before the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription publiſhed, having attained to a right that was acquired and not ſucceeding his father as the laſt poſſeſſor, but the firſt purchaſer, by the feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dall and fundamentall law. For a proſcription, as, <hi>Andraeas Gailius (a great Civilian, and laterall Iudge of the Imperiall Chamber, Counſellour unto two Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and ſometimes advocate for the Duke of Bavaria ſaith, &amp; proveth, Lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de pace publica. obſer.</hi> 15. <hi>num.</hi> 19. is perſonall, and dies with the perſon. and <hi>obſer. ultima. n.</hi> 32. the Ban (ſaith hee) ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires
<pb facs="tcp:2838:40"/>
with the death of the outlawed, <hi>per L.</hi> the crime, or puniſhment of the father can lay no ble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh upon the ſonne. 26. <hi>&amp; ibi.</hi> Nor can he bee made ſucceſſor of another mans offence. <hi>D. de poe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis, &amp; per L. defuncto. D. de publicis judiciis. &amp; per L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; final. C. ſi reus vel accuſatus morinus fuerit adde L. publica.</hi> 3. <hi>D. de publicis judiciis, &amp; allegat. infr.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, he ſhould be compelled to confeſſe and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, that hee is no Prince of the Empire, becauſe he hath need to bee admitted into that or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der. But they who doe not eſteeme him for a Prince of Germany, that is, of the Empire, muſt needs praeſuppoſe him, either to have beene a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtard, or ſprung of ſome obſcure Race, and that his Parents were not Princes, unleſſe, they would call him a Prince of England, or Spaine, or France, or ſome other Empire: but this is falfe (unleſſe that he may bee deſervedly ſtiled a Prince of England as being a Prince of that royall blood) as the other is diabolicall. The rights of blood <hi>(inquit lex)</hi> cannot be taken away by any Civill Law, <hi>by which the Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawrie is brought in, L. jura.</hi> 8. <hi>D. de regul. juris. L. jus agnation.</hi> 34. <hi>D. depactis.</hi> The ſonne of the proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed Prince of Anhalt, though taken priſoner in the battell of Prague, never needed to be reſtored againe to the dignity of Princes; but ever, even in his captivity becauſe himſelfe was not proſcribed nor could the Ban of his Father, by any law, bee of force againſt him, he was alwaies accounted, and called a Prince, even by Caeſar, and the Imperialiſts
<pb facs="tcp:2838:40"/>
though, his Father was not yet diſcharged of his proſcription; So alſo, the ſonnes of <hi>Iohn Fredrick,</hi> Elector of Saxony, were accounted amongſt the Princes, and acknowledged for Dukes of Saxony, and ſo ſtiled, though their father, was then pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, and in captivity. And now, who can deny that the children of King <hi>Fredericke,</hi> the Counts Palatine, that is, Princes of the Empire, ſhould be acknowledged, for perſonages of that dignitie? The Emperour himſelfe calles them by no other name, nor otherwiſe can he call them. But it is ſufficiently knowne, what it is to be a Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine in the Empire, and ſprung from the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall houſe of the Palatine. This name and title belongs to no other man, nor is given to any, but him onely that is a Prince: To be ſtiled the Count Palatine, and reckoned amongſt the Counts Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, is all one as to be a Prince of the Empire, in ſuch a ranke, and degree as by the order of the Empire is granted, to the Counts Palatine, which are the firſt and chiefe amongſt other Princes. The title of Count Palatine is of a higher eſteeme in the Empire than that of Duke and Prince. And therefore in the marſhaling of their titles and dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, the Princes Palatine preferre the name of Count Palatine before the title of a Duke. Are not the Children of King <hi>Fredericke,</hi> ſonnes to the Neece of the King of Denmarke, by his Siſter? Are they not Princes of the royall blood of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land? If they had nothing elſe to ſhow, but this
<pb facs="tcp:2838:41"/>
prerogative of birth, and the ſplendour of their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers linage ſhould adde no honour to them, who could deny that they were Princes? who durſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to diſpute and take away this privilege from them, derived unto them from their mother, their Grand-mother, and their Great Grand-mother, all, both Queenes themſelves, and Kings daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for any ſentence againſt their father? And therefore, by what law, or ground is it ordered that <hi>Charles Lodowicke,</hi> the Electour, borne Count Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, and that, litle leſſe than three yeeres before his father was proſcribed, ſhould need to bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored into the number and degree of the Princes of the Empire? It is great cruelty, to compell the ſonne by his owne confeſſion, and acknowledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, to iudge and declare his owne father, whom in his ſoule and conſcience he doth conclude guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, for a Rebell, Enemy, and Traytor to Caeſar: but, more cruelty if he be conſtrained, and enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, to confeſſe himſelfe an offender, who is no way conſcious, of any offence, nor by reaſon of his infancy, could doe any, and ſo deprive himſelfe of his priviledges, dignity, and prerogative of his parentage.</p>
            <p>But it being granted (which can never be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved) that the father was a moſt hainous offendor, and had committed rebellion, and treaſon, in the higheſt degree, and was therefore juſtly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to baniſhment, and deprived of all rights and priviledges, yet this ſentence ought to be no plea
<pb facs="tcp:2838:41"/>
in barre, againſt his children, conceived and borne before ſentence of their fathers proſcription, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, in thoſe things, which concerne that digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, which was borne with them, their privilege of nobilitie, and ſuch things as deſcend not from the perſon of the father, but are due unto the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by right of blood, the right of their family, by the covenant, and tranſmiſſion of their fore-fathers, and by the diſpoſition of the Law; as are the Electorate, and the Principalitie of the Empire, that is, the royall, antient Fees, which come not by name of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, nor by ſucceſſion of the father, but by right of the firſt and Simultaneous inveſtiture, and the grant of the firſt acquirer. <hi>c.</hi> 1. §. <hi>poſtea vero, &amp; gloſſ. in. d c. §. cum vero. Conradus in verbo. frater. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>de fend. tit.</hi> 1. <hi>De his qui feudum dare poſſunt. Baldus ad Rubric. de ſucceſsion. feudi ad §. Hoc quoque n.</hi> 4. The ſonne, <hi>ſaith he,</hi> comes not in as a common heire; but by right of blood which is unchangeable. <hi>&amp; in c.</hi> 1. § <hi>finali. Evae fuit prima cauſa benefic. amittendi.</hi> By birth-right <hi>(ſaith he)</hi> forme of inveſtiture being ſet down by the Lord, from the tenor wherof there muſt be no variation) the ſon ſucceedeth in the fee. <hi>Iulius Clarus prime Chancellour to the King of Spaine, &amp; regent in the province of Millain lib.</hi> 4. <hi>ſentent. feudum. q.</hi> 66. <hi>proveth that</hi> the crime of the Father doth not exclude the ſon from the antient fee, <hi>&amp; lib</hi> 5. <hi>ſent.</hi> § <hi>laeſae Maieſtatis. n.</hi> 10. that the puniſhment of the Father for high treaſon is of no force, againſt the children, which are borne, and conceived be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:2838:42"/>
their fathers treſpaſſe; <hi>upon which Baiardus no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth,</hi> that the Fathers puniſhment is praejudiciall to the children only in thoſe things, which deſcend to them from the perſon of their father, not in other things, as namely thoſe fees, to which they ſucceed by covenant and proviſoes. <hi>Adde hereunto Boerius who deciſion. part.</hi> 1. <hi>q.</hi> 10. <hi>n.</hi> 6 <hi>affirmeth that</hi> the ſonnes for the Fathers offence cannot be deprived of the eſtate ſetled upon them before the offence done, that the ſentence hath no force againſt them, which are borne before, but onely after the offence committed. <hi>Cynus in d. l. Quiſquis. Alciate who Conſil.</hi> 467. <hi>n.</hi> by the common received opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on denyeth that the ſentence concerneth thoſe children, who are lawfully conceived, and borne, before the treſpaſſe done, <hi>Adde alſo Couarruvias, Grammaticus, Gailius, Mynſingerus, Baldus, Bartolus, Iſernias, Alvareta. Bartholm Camerarius, Rolandinus de valle conſ.</hi> 74 <hi>lib.</hi> 3. <hi>and infinite others of the ſame opinion</hi> But theſe inſuing lawes are moſt remarkeable. <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>D. de interdictis, relegatis &amp; deportatis.</hi> Thoſe eſtates which deſcend not from the father, but are given by the Linage, the State, and the nature of the things themſelves, remaine undeſtayned to the children, though the father bee baniſhed or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>c. de libertis, &amp; eorum filiis, it is ſaid ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely, that</hi> the faults of the parents cannot im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach thoſe children, which are knowne to bee borne, whilſt their parents were at libertie. <hi>l. Eman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipatum a patre</hi> 7. §. <hi>l. &amp;</hi> 2. §. <hi>D. de ſenat. ibi.</hi> If any one
<pb facs="tcp:2838:42"/>
be conceived, before his father (for a crime) be put out of the Senate, though he be not borne, till the father have loſt his dignity, (w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> is more) he ſhall be eſteemed as the Sonne of a Senatour; for the time of conception is to bee reſpected, <hi>&amp;</hi> §. 2. <hi>in d. l. it is ſaid,</hi> that the dignity of the Grand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>father, doth more availe, than the fall of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can hinder the ſonne; <hi>and l. filium familias.</hi> 9. <hi>D. eodem.</hi> An acquired dignity, cannot be taken from children, for the fathers fault, though he be thruſt out of the ſenate <hi>l. qui ad tempus.</hi> 2. §. 3. <hi>&amp;</hi> 4. <hi>de decurionibus &amp; filiis eorum, where it is ſaid,</hi> that though the father, after the conception of the ſonne, doe loſe his dignity, the ſonne ſhall not loſe his. <hi>Alſo.</hi> §. 4. That he who ſhall be borne after his fathers baniſhment, and proſcription, if he was conceived before it, ſhall bee reputed the ſonne of a Senator. Feudall goods, <hi>ſaith Andraeas Gailius l.</hi> 2. <hi>de pace public. obſerv.</hi> 25. <hi>n.</hi> 33. (the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed perſon being dead,) ought to be reſtored, to his ſonnes, and other kinſmen; becauſe the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of a father and a kinſman, cannot praejudice the ſonnes and kinſmen, in the ancient fee, which is by covenant, and providence <hi>and n.</hi> 34. the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed party being dead, the ancient fee, and belonging to the family, returneth to the heires of his blood, for whom by the covenant, and promiſe of the firſt archievour, that liberty was obtained; and againſt whom the offence of a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or a kinſman, can bee no impediment. But
<pb facs="tcp:2838:43"/>
of theſe things we have diſcourſed fully, at large, and purpoſely, in our booke <hi>Devindicius cauſae Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinae,</hi> whether wee referre the reader; in the meane time it is to be deteſted, that every com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon perſon promiſcuouſly, though of the loweſt ranke, doth enjoy the benefit, and may bee ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by theſe lawes; yet the children of Princes ſhall be denyed this ordinary juſtice, and become of a more unhappy condition than others in that reſpect. But to the matter.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>Caeſar</hi> offers to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore the Count Palatine, into part of his ancient dominions, not to be deſpiſed.</p>
            <p>Now it is to be conſidered, that this part is not named, nor expreſſed, nor intimated, of what quality, and quantity it ſhall bee. It onely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pends upon the interpretation, and judgement of the Imperaliſts, whether, it bee ſuch as may not be eſteemed to be deſpiſed. If they account of it, according to the eſtimation of the condition, in which they place the Electour, they will eſteeme a ſmall portion to be a great one. But that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure, will bee ſo ſmall, and contemptible, that it will bee ignominious, and bring great prejudice upon the King and the Electour, to accept it. Indeed, by the laſt declaration, which
<pb facs="tcp:2838:43"/>
was exhibited to the Ambaſſadour, it appeareth, and is to be plainely ſeene, that both the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dignity, and office, the chiefeſt, and greateſt thing appertaining to this reſtitution; and alſo the upper Palatinate, a portion, equall to that which is left to be reſtored in the lower Palatinate, is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided, and ſeparated from reſtitution, for, there it is ſaid, that neither of theſe muſt bee menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, or hoped for, as long as any of the Bavarian Line is ſurviving. Onely, of that part, which the Bavarian, and Spaniard hold, on the Lower Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, by way of gage or pledge; ſome hope is given, that it may bee reſtored under certaine conditions, when thoſe Bankers are paied. But this part, (if you take from thence the Signio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries belonging to <hi>Lodowicke Phillip</hi> Duke of Sym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meren, the Electours fathers brother, and the goods aſſigned to the Electreſſe <hi>Lodovica</hi> Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe Palatine his Grandmother, and the Queene <hi>Elizabeth</hi> widowes, for their dowries it would be very ſmall, and of little eſtimation. But if you alſo divide from thence the fields, grounds, Cities, and townes given, granted, and delivered to <hi>Leopald</hi> of Auſtria, the Biſhop of Ments, Wormbes &amp; Spiers, the Maſter of the Knights of the Teutonicke or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, the Landgrave of Darmſtar, &amp; others, it would be far leſſe: for of theſe, there is no mention made by <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and therfore it can not be preſumed, that theſe ſhall be computed, in the reſtitution of that no deſpicable portion. And now it is alſo to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:44"/>
that it is not to be added and expreſſed, when, &amp; under what conditions, that epitomized portion ought to be delivered. This ought firſt to have beene agreed upon; for it might eaſily come to paſſe, that ſuch intollerable, unjuſt, and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full conditions might be preſcribed him as the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour with his honour, and conſcience, could not condeſcend unto, which might as well im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peach the receaved religion, the Church diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, and ſtate, as the forme of adminiſtring, and governing the Common-wealth, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraine them, to new and ſtricter lawes. Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onleſſe the Spaniards, and Bavarian will never deliver up, what they hold by ſtrength in the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate, unleſſe they firſt receive in hand thoſe emoluments, and profits, which they pretend, and require for their rompenſation, and ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; the rates whereof, they well know how to inhaunce, at their pleaſure. The Spaniards in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, as formerly they have pretended, deſire a promiſe, and performance of a league, and helpe from the Engliſh againſt the Dutch, and French, and the protection, and convoy of their owne navie, threatning withall, that they will not, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, reſtore their part in the Palatinate, but upon theſe, and the like conditions. The Bavarian, who (as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> ſpeakes of one) regards nothing elſe, but how hee may ſtill get more, will crave a ſumme of money, and that no ſmall one. Therefore this part, whatſoever it is,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:44"/>
will coſt deare, and a price not to be ſpoken of, and yet if the preſent deſolation and vaſtation of the fields in the Palatinate, the depopulation of the Countrey, the ruine of their Villages and Townes, and the dwelling houſes burned to aſhes be conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered; it may bee accounted of no value, or eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>It is further alſo to bee conſidered, that the Prince Electour, without prejudice of his right, and the violation of the fundamentall law, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not conſent to any partition, or acceptation of ſome one part: becauſe in the Golden Bull, by a ſpeciall decree, in divers places, and in emphati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call words often repeateds all diviſion, diſtraction and diſmembring is forbidden: and it is alſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by a royall decree, that the Electorall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, ſhall bee ſo conjoyned, and connexed to the Territory of the Palatinate, that the one by no meanes may bee ever ſevered from the other. If therfore now he ſhould accept of any part, by way of partition, and diviſion, he muſt conſent and alſo acknowledge, that the Electorall dignity, may by ſome meanes, be ſeparated either from the whole, or part of the Palatinate, which yet hee cannot doe, without prejudice of his title, and entire reſtitution, unleſſe perhaps, ſome integrall part; that is, the whole lower Palatinate, to which the dignity is annexed, ſhould bee reſtored; nor that neither, but with this condition, that his title and hope of obtaining the reſt, may ſtill
<pb facs="tcp:2838:45"/>
abide intire and uncontroverted. For, then the partition and diviſion cannot be ſaid to continue perpetuall, but rather a ſuſpenſion of the intire re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution and Confederation. But, the meaning and ſcope of the Emperor and Bavarian, and their Subjects, is far from ſuch a moderation and advice, as is moſt apparent; not only by the laſt anſwere, but by other declarations and often experience.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the Emperour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, That he, according as it ſhall be agreed, will inveſt him. But, now it is to be underſtood, that this inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is reſtrained, only to that part which is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be reſtored, as <hi>Radoldus</hi> the Internuncio for the Emperour into England, hath plainely decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; but not to be extended to the whole Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, and the Office of Arch-Sewer thereunto annexed. But the Prince Electour, cannot with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his great prejudice, accept of ſuch an Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as is limited and reſtrained to one part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe by that act he ſhould be excluded and paſſed over in the generall, principall, and ſimultaneous inveſtiture, which of right belongs to all the males of that Stocke: in reſpect of the whole Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, the coherent Dignity, and the depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dances <hi>c. nonne praeſumt.</hi> Hee, that is not comprehended expreſly
<pb facs="tcp:2838:45"/>
in this common Inveſtiture, can pretend no Title of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsion and obtaining the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate and Electorall Office. There is none of the Counts Palatine, but may ground his Title, and hope for ſucceſsion in the Palatinate, and the Electorall Dignity, upon this Inveſtiture. For this Inveſtiture doth give a title, cauſe, action, hope, and pretence of ſucceeding in the Fees. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>Quibus modis feud. conſt. poſſ. c.</hi> 1. <hi>in princ. de ſucceſſ. fratrum. c.</hi> 1. <hi>in fine de f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udo cognat. c. Si facta. Si de feud. defuncti controv. ſit inter D. &amp; agnatos Vaſalli.</hi> An Inveſtiture is a kind of ſetling in poſſeſsion. <hi>Myſing. conſ.</hi> 64. <hi>n.</hi> 10. and hath the force of a Contract, or rather is a Contract of it ſelfe, <hi>Menoch. conſ.</hi> 101. <hi>n.</hi> 28. <hi>Conſil.</hi> 103 <hi>n.</hi> 53. and thereby the ſonnes and kindred have a firme title and aſſurance, which, without their owne act, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not afterwards be made void, as <hi>Weſenbecius</hi> affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth, <hi>Conſ.</hi> 41. <hi>n.</hi> 103. <hi>in fine.</hi> Beſides it confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth the title in ancient Fees, though the incum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent hold it by an unjuſt poſſeſsion. <hi>Vlcius Zazi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us conſ.</hi> 1 <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 24. <hi>Tiraquell in tract. Le mort ſaiſit le vit. declarat.</hi> 7. <hi>poſt.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 15. <hi>&amp;</hi> 16. <hi>Weſenb. conſ,</hi> 1. <hi>vol.</hi> 1. <hi>n</hi> 49. <hi>ita citat Nicolaus Burgundus in lib. de E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectoratu Bavarico.</hi> Therefore, it behoovs the Prince Elector to deale warily, and circumſpectly in this buſineſſe, by endeavouring to obtaine the Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture;
<pb facs="tcp:2838:46"/>
that is, the renovation of the ancient and common inveſtiture, uſed in the Palatine family, for himſelfe, as the head of the family, and his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinſmen; no way permitting that the Inveſtiture may be omitted, or himſelfe, or the reſt which are to be inveſted, be paſſed over.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, the Emperour of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, that when it ſhall come to a Treaty, concerning the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctorall Dignity, and the other poſtulates, he will obſerve ſuch moderation, that in thoſe things which may bee gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon reaſonable Conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, both the moſt Illuſtrious King, may know ſome ſignes of the good affection of his Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall Maieſty towards Him, and the Count Palatine may finde the inclination of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour towards him. But it is to bee
<pb facs="tcp:2838:46"/>
obſerved; That, this Caeſarean ſuppoſition, is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready cancelled and abrogated by his owne two laſt anſweres. For, in them it is ſaid plainely, That the Emperours diſpoſalls of the Dignities and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions of the Electour Palatine, are confirmed by the late Treaty of <hi>Prague,</hi> and conſequently al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed of by all the Princes of the Empire. And yet by thoſe diſpoſals, which in the records of that Treaty they have provided alwayes to be of force, all hope of ever attaining the Electorate and the annexed Provinces, is taken away and cut off from the children of King <hi>Frederick:</hi> it being plainely there expreſſed; that by thoſe diſpoſals, the Electorate is conferred and delivered, not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to the Duke of Bavaria, but alſo to the Line of <hi>William,</hi> that is, to the race of is Father (of which there are five males yet remaining) for ever.</p>
            <p>Which very thing is more plainely and cleere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly delivered in the other laſt anſwere; where his Imperiall Majeſtie doth confeſſe and moſt plaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhow, that he hath granted, (not onely to the Duke of Bavaria, but alſo to the Line of <hi>William</hi>) as well the Electorall dignitie, as the upper Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinate, by an hereditary right; and therefore no treatie concerning their reſtitution, ſo long as any of that line ſurvived, might be admitted. By this then it appeares plainely, that the hope of obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Electorall dignitie, and upper Palatinate is not only cut off from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he branches, but from the very ſtocke? With what confidence then, upon
<pb facs="tcp:2838:47"/>
what ground, by what pretence, can the treatie about the reſtitution of the Palatinate be continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed? Indeed it was afterward ſignified that upon adviſe with the Electorall Colledge, which was intereſſed in the matter, ſome meanes were diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered by which hopes were given, that though the Bavarian line of <hi>William</hi> was yet in being, the difficulty, concerning the Electorall dignity, might be over paſſed, and ſome more ample ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction given to the moſt illuſtrious King of great Britaine. But there is none, that will uſe his rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but may obſerve to what end, theſe reports were raiſed, and deviſed. For they are grounded upon no probabilitie, but tend meerely to enſnare and illaqueate with vaine and empty ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches the King of Great Britaine, and all thoſe who are intereſſed in the Palatine cauſe, that they might not proclaime warre, take hold of occaſions, and ſo joyne with the French, Swedes, and other enemies of the houſe of Auſtria. Such policies are ordinary in the Courts of Caeſar, and the Spaniard; as may bee proved by many examples. Indeed their Legates have learned this leſſon ſo per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly, that amongſt forraigne Nations, they have not undeſervedly gotten, the name and fame of great politicians.</p>
            <p>But (I pray tell me) what meanes can be found, that ſatisfaction may bee given to the right, and moſt juſt claime of <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> the Electour, his brethren, and kinſmen on the one ſide; and the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:47"/>
ambition, and inſatiable deſire of the Bavarian on the other? Only one muſt be Electour, and keepe that dignitie; two cannot ſit in that ſeat of Iuſtice, nor performe the office of one man, nor ſpeake with one tongue, nor give one vote. The ſeaven Electours, like ſeaven pillars, ſupport the ſtate of the Germane Common-wealth. If there be more or fewer, the Symmetrie and bulke of that buil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding muſt needs fall. The Golden Bull, which is the Royall fundamentall law, and princely decree, admitteth only of ſeaven, and to each of them aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignes, and preſcribes his office, principalitie, and power, to which the Electorate is annexed: hence alſo, it ſtiles them the ſeaven candle-ſtickes, the number of which can neither be augmented, nor diminiſhed, without diſmembring and ſubverting of the body of the Republique. If there were more, as nine, or eleaven, (for the number muſt naturally bee uneven, leſt the voices being even, there might happen a diviſion, and ſchiſme in the election of a king) what places, what prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, what offices, beſeeming their high dignity, could be appointed to them? What lands, and provinces for the ſetling the Electorate, could be aſſigned to them? So great is the authority of the Golden Bull, that it cannot be altered and viola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Emperour, though with the conſent of the Electours; unleſſe by overthrowing the lawes, that is, by racing the foundation, he would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert and ruinate the ſtate and conſtitution of the Commonwealth.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:48"/>But if it ſhould happen, that nine Electours ſhould be created, how can they be marſhalled in their proper ranks and order? (the Palatine ſurely will not ſuffer himſelfe to bee diſplaced, and put by of his right and poſſeſſion, confirmed, by the cuſtome of many ages, by the fundamentall Laws, and by the conſent of ſo many Emperours, and all the Princes; becauſe he cannot doe this, without impeaching his honour, and wrong of his conſcience, nor yet without reproach and injury to his whole family. For, ſo he ſhould ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge, and by his giving place and example make it publikely appeare, that He is juſtly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his ancient and acquired right, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative which time out of minde did appertaine unto Him, among the Electours; and accept it as a great favour, that he ſhould bee admitted as a new creature, and an Electour upon the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of intreaty: when yet with leſſe diſparage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and indignity Hee might better renounce the whole Electorate, then conſent unto ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honourable a change of precedency and order, into the loweſt rancke; which would bee a ſigne of a fooliſh and puſillaminous ambition. The Bavarian likewiſe, will by no meanes ſuffer him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe to be removed from the place, into which he hath aſcended, with ſo great, and fervent de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, fury, and violence; with ſo much labour, and ſweat, with ſo much effuſion of blood, and long continuation of Armes; and which he hath
<pb facs="tcp:2838:48"/>
ſnatched away by force, and conferred upon his family. Although a new Electour ought to ſit in the loweſt place, and not to be eſteemed of higher eminency, then any other; and yet ſuch is his ambition, and ſo high are the thoughts of his aſpiring minde, that he makes no bones to contend for principality, not onely, with the Electours farre more ancient then himſelfe, but with <hi>Caeſar</hi> himſelfe alſo, as appeares, by the experience of many former yeeres, when hee compelled <hi>Caeſar,</hi> at the meeting at Ratisbone, to diſcharge <hi>Wallinſten</hi> of his office, and to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove all the other things, which he then deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. Long before that the Bavarian was placed by <hi>Caeſar</hi> among the Electours, even in the times of the Emperours <hi>Rodolph,</hi> and <hi>Matthias,</hi> he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with the Arch-Dukes of Auſtria, for the firſt and more honourable place, he did ambitiou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſly affect the title of ſoveraignty, as well as the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrians, &amp; in fine conſtrained <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> who then wanted his aſſiſtance, to give him that, title, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was made a new Elector. It is true indeed, that the Dukes of Bavaria poſſeſſed of the eſtate, and chiefe of their family, made ſome ſcruple, to give place to the Arch-Dukes of Auſtria, (which were not advanced to regall, and Imperiall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity) in the aſſemblies, and parliaments of the Empire, profeſſing themſelves to be more anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Dukes, and that it was unlawfull, for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours derived from the Auſtrian family, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre
<pb facs="tcp:2838:49"/>
their poſteritie before the Bavarian family, which long time had enjoyed the priviledge of the chiefe ſeate, (by making them Arch-Dukes) becauſe alſo, the Duke of Bavaria (as the more worthy held the prime collaterall place amongſt the ſecular Princes, and ſubſcribed to, and ſigned the Decrees and Lawes propounded and confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in the Parliaments by the Princes; when the Auſtrians, who diſdained to be placed inferiour to the Bavarian, did ſit collaterally with the Priors, Prelates and Eccleſiaſticall perſons. But yet ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver any of the Bavarians did ſtand ſo much upon it, and prevaile ſo farre in it, with ſuch eagerneſſe, ambition, and better ſucceſſe, as this moderne Duke; who above all the reſt, endeavours to preſerve the ancient ſplendor and dignity of his Family.</p>
            <p>But they ſay it is probable, and there is ſome hope, that the Bavarians my be perſwaded to conſent to a covenant of alternation, on this wiſe; that after the death of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Bavarian, now poſſeſſing it, the Electorall Dignity and Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, may be performed and held by exchange of turnes, betwixt the firſt borne ſons and Nephews of him, and the firſt borne Sons and Nephews of King <hi>Frederick</hi> Palatine: that for default of either of their iſſue, the whole Electorate may be totally left, as by right of accrewment, to the longeſt liver. But theſe are muſhrumes and quillits, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out root or ground, invented onely to circumvent
<pb facs="tcp:2838:49"/>
and enſnare the minds of the credulous. For the Bavarians now being powerfull, and having their eſtate ſetled, and withall, of eminent authority and grace in the Empire, are ſo farre from conde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcending to ſuch a Covenant, that they will not connive and permit, that the controverſie of the Electorate ſhould either be ſet apart, or left in ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſe. The right of either party being reſerved, or that it be referred to a Treaty or a competent Iudge, as they have openly and with great earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe publiſhed and declared; as at other meetings, ſo more eſpecially in the Diet at Ratisbone; and they have alſo by their urgent importunity, preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Emperour ſo farre, that the Palatines of <hi>Rolerts</hi> Race ſhall ſtill remaine excluded from hope and poſſeſſion of the Electorate; nor ſhall it be permitted to them, to queſtion their Title to it, ſo long as any of the Bavarian Line of <hi>William</hi> ſurvives, and is alive: but, that they ſhall bee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled to renounce all their title, and give a cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they will move no more for that cauſe hereafter in the Empire: which unleſſe they doe, neither Germany, nor the Bavarians, can have any aſſurance of peace and ſecurity. For (ſay they) if the Palatines have leave and liberty to demand their right, then, ſo ſoone as occaſion and ſupply of meanes ſhall favour them (both which upon their re-entry and reſtitution to their dominions they will provide and obtaine) they will not bee quiet againe, till they have chaſed the Bavarians from
<pb facs="tcp:2838:50"/>
the Electorate, as the ſonnes and Grand-children of Rodolph have done, who have broken the transaction, and covenant for their alternall fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Electorall office, concluded of in the Papian treaty, and by force and fraud have thruſt out the children, and poſterity of <hi>Lodowicke</hi> the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian Emperour from their poſſeſſion.</p>
            <p>It is therefore neceſſary, that firſt, and before the Palatines be admitted into the Empire, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to their Principalities this queſtion be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined, and tranſacted abſolutely, which other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, would kindle the fire of new troubles, in a freſh warre, and by conſequent, the empire, and the Common-wealth, ſhould enjoy no ſecure, and firme peace, but be diſquieted with perpetuall feare. Thus they conclude, and (as they judge) de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termine, what they had adviſed of, and decreed from the beginning. And hence it came to paſſe, that with much ſubtiltie, threats, and Oratory they have not only procured the perpetuall ſucceſſion of the Bavarian Line in the Electorate, and the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of the Palatine family, to be recorded into the Inſtruments of Prague, amongſt the conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of that diſhonorable peace, but, have alſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled the Emperour, with their importunity, to cut off from the Palatines, all hope of obtaining the Electorate, and upper Palatinate, by proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming, and writing confidently, and abſolutely, that he may not permit, that, there ſhould be any demand or conference, or meeting, about their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:50"/>
as long, as the male Line of <hi>William</hi> the Bavarian, was in being. But, goe to, let them ſay, and make oath, that they would conſent to this al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternation, and ſucceſſive execution by turnes; is it tolerable that <hi>Charles Lodowicke,</hi> an Electour borne by his owne birth-right, and by the law, proviſion, and tradition of his Anceſtours; and that his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren and kinſmen, for whom this right was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured, ſhould condeſcend to ſuch a condition as would both bring ſcandall to Himſelfe, and his Countrey, and alſo infringe their ancient privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledges, and prerogatives. With what credit, with what honeſtie, with what pretence can hee be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced that hee ſhould enfeeble, leſſen and divide his owne Right and poſſeſſion, which hath beene ratified and eſtabliſhed by the preterition of ſo many ages, by the Confirmation of ſo many Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perours, in a word, by the approbation of all ſtates throughout the whole world (who have lived ſince the firſt time of ſetling of a Common-wealth) &amp; that for the favour of a moſt ingratefull and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous Familie? Who can endure, who would not ſtomacke and ſtorme, if he ſhould ſee the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Princes, who formerly have beene ſo carefull to preſerve the ancient lawes and ordinances of their Countrey, who have adventured to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goe any hazard, though it were of life and ſtate, for the maintenance of their liberty of the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bull, and other conſtitutions and fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall decrees now ſo diſhonourably and unadviſed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:2838:51"/>
to diſſolue and violate them? Hath not this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant of alternation, which the Bavarians, even three Ages ſince, did preſume to bring in, been ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogated by the Golden Bull of <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth, by the Confirmation of ſucceeding Emperours, by the inviolable cuſtome of ſo many yeeres, as an evill preſident, which might tend to the decay and ruine of the Empire, would foſter diſcord and difference amongſt the Princes, and be an occaſion of continuall broiles and tumults.</p>
            <p>From theſe things (which yet have beene but onely touched) it doth appeare what may bee judged of thoſe meanes which are propounded for the overcomming of that difficultie, concerning the reſtitution of the Electorall dignitie: for, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the ſucceſſion and execution by interchange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able turnes be propounded, or whether two new ones, to bee added to the ſeaven Ancients bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved on, both the one and the other is not to bee entertained, becauſe it cannot bee effected and brought to paſſe with any reaſon, ſecurity and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit. Let them therefore ſpeake, promiſe, offer, or ſweare what they will, it is certaine and manifeſt, that Caeſar, the Bavarians and their aſſociates, will never receive <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> the Electour, or his brethren, and kinſmen unto their ancient ſtate of dignitie and fortunes; nor will they permit them to attaine to any power, which may be any wayes formidable unto them, leſt when occaſion ſerves, aide being ſent them from every ſide, they ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:2838:51"/>
uſe it to revenge, and the recovery of thoſe things which are taken from them. Briefly, it is cleare and evident, that all labour and time is ſpent in vaine, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>t this time, and ſo long as the Bavarian is alive and the ſecond Prince in the whole Empire; it be yet hoped, that by friendly treaties it may be effected, that the Electorall Palatinate, with the dignity and ſeptemvirall Robes ſhould be intirely reſtored upon equall tearmes. Some other policy therefore muſt be thought of ſome other courſe muſt be taken, ſome alteration of times is to bee looked for, that ſo theſe invincible ſpirits, puffed up with the ſucceſſe of their affaires, and growne inſolent with their long felicitie, and inveterate authoritie, may at length be made to know them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and brought to more mild and moderate counſels.</p>
            <p>And theſe are the propoſalls which are offered by Caeſar, and willed to bee accepted as a ſpeciall grace and favour of the Emperour, and which are (by them) eſteemed to deſerve a more neare tyall of familiaritie and league, with other offices of love, betwixt the King of Great Britaine and the Houſe of Auſtria. But now it is to be conſidered upon what Conditions this favour by which the moſt Illuſtrious King, may apprehend the willing Inclination, and benevolent affection of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour towards Him, and his clemencie towards his Nephewes; may be granted.</p>
            <p>The Conditions, I warrant you, are expreſſely
<pb facs="tcp:2838:52"/>
ſet downe <hi>but all</hi> and thoſe likewiſe which are yet to be treated of, <hi>are ſhuffled together under the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of making a League,</hi> as it is in the anſwer.</p>
            <p>And indeed, the firſt Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion requires, that the Count Palatine doe humbly ſue for the benefit of reconciliation, by humbling and ſubmitting him ſelfe to his ſacred Imperiall Maieſtie in a ſubmiſsive man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner as beſeemeth him. Here the Electour is enjoyned to ſtand and confeſſe himſelfe to be guiltie, and by his owne fact declare publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, that he is not innocent, but that he hath offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his Imperiall Majeſtie to whom hee ought to be reconciled. A reconciliation doth preſuppoſe an offence: But in what did he ever offend the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour? Whether, becauſe hee came into the world? whether, becauſe hee liveth? whether, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee was in his minoritie and could injure no man by reaſon of his infancie? whether, becauſe he is deſcended of the ancient and Royall ſtocke of the Palatines, and borne of a Queene his mother? whether becauſe he had a father who was elected King of Bohemia? whether, becauſe he was brought
<pb facs="tcp:2838:52"/>
up at Leyden, and applyed himſelfe to the ſtudies of Arts? whether, becauſe hee was quiet, and did forbeare Armes? whether becauſe he following the councell of the King his Uncle, was not a Partie? whether becauſe he humbly and ſubmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſively deſired his reſtitution and inveſtiture of Caeſar? Whether, becauſe he hath tendred him all obſequie, and obſervance? Whether becauſe the King his Uncle in his behalfe did ſend an Ambaſſadour to the Emperour and his Electours? whether becauſe by the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, hee is the Grand-child of King <hi>Iames,</hi> and by the ſiſter, the Nephew of King <hi>Charles,</hi> and the Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phews Sonne of the King of Denmarke, and kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to the King of France? Some ſuch thing muſt be, which hath given the offence: But why is not the offence, and the cauſe thereof, expreſſed, for which he muſt ſhew ſuch a kind of ſubmiſſion and humiliation, as is not uſually required, nor per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, but by delinquents and ſuch as acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge themſelves to be great offenders? Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore is there not a word mentioned why <hi>Caeſar</hi> is ſo offended with him, that hee muſt needes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come a Suppliant, by ſeeking with ſo much humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, the benefit of his reconciliation?</p>
            <p>Secondly, He is bound to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce all Leagues and Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants
<pb facs="tcp:2838:53"/>
whatſoever, which either He Himſelfe, or haply His Father, hath made with any Kings or States whatſoever, as well within, as without the Empire. Heere he is enjoyned to bid farewell, for ever, to all Aſſiſtants and friends; and ſolely to reſt upon the meere favour of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and to lay the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his hope and fortunes upon thoſe uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and doubtfull propoſitions. But, by this meanes, he ſhould not onely injure, and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly ingratefull towards his better friends and acquaintance, who have entertained Him, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, Mother, Brethren and Siſters exiled, and hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto have preſerved them ſafe, as in a Sanctuary, and accumulated them with all kind of Curteſies and friendly offices; but alſo, he ſhould deprive himſelfe ever hereafter, of the power and liberty of looking for &amp; contracting leagues and friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, or entertaining Commerce and familiarity with whom he pleaſeth. It is neither wiſedome nor ſafety to leave certaineties with diſhonour, and prejudice, both to Conſcience and Credit; and to turne unto uncertainties which are both hurtfull and infamous, with diſgrace and ruine. How miſerable would be the condition, I will not ſay of a Prince, but of a Peaſant, who muſt ſuffer
<pb facs="tcp:2838:53"/>
himſelfe to be bound to ſo hard and unjuſt condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, that he ſhould quite diſable himſelfe of all hopes of uſing occaſions &amp; favours of his friends? There is no example extant, in which, ſo gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, abſolute, and indiſtinct renunciation of all leagues and covenants, hath beene required of any Prince of Germany, who hath hitherto beene reſtored unto favour.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, there muſt be ſatiſfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction alſo given in other things, of which it ſhall be determined here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, in a future Treatiſe concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning a league, to bee made with His Imperiall Majeſty, the King of Spaine, and the whole Houſe of Auſtria. Hence it is collected, that yet there are ſome other conditions to be exacted of the Electour, and preſcribed to him. In all thoſe there muſt firſt be ſatisfaction given in very deed, and a league confirmed by the King of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, with the whole Houſe of Auſtria, and many other offices, emoluments, and aſſiſtance to bee granted according to the arbitrement and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeall of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Spaniard; and then, the Emperour promiſeth He will performe his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:54"/>Theſe are things which the Emperour offreth, and the conditions upon which they are offred. And now if theſe offers be conſidered by them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and in their owne nature, without the conditions annexed, they are ſuch as will not onely bring no honour, profit and benefit, but rather ignominy, loſſe, and prejudice to him that accepts and conſents unto them. They are alſo unbeſeeming the greatneſſe of the Imperiall Majeſty, willingly and yet hardly, offering ſo ſmall things, with ſo great exaggeration, and as it were exprobation. Moreover they are farre unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of the honour of the King, who did require them, and had deſerved better; to whom it would be a diſhonour, if ſo many interceſſions, &amp; Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, if ſo much expenſe of ſtate in theſe attempts, if his great kindneſſe ſhewed to the Auſtrians, his owne friendſhip and confederation with them, if the moderation, which Himſelfe, and the King His Father, have manifeſted in the behalfe of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Houſe of Auſtria, in the midſt of theſe combuſtions; if the continuall profits, which the Spaniards get by England, could procure, obtaine, and merit no more than ſome one part of the Palatinate, not to bee contemned. Surely, theſe men either make ſmall account of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert, league, ſociety and friendſhip of the King, if they thinke it may bee recompenſed with ſome ſhall portion of the Palatinate, already exhau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, and utterly ruinated; or elſe, they valew
<pb facs="tcp:2838:54"/>
that portion, and the favour of the Emperour at ſo high a rate, that the friendſhip of ſo potent a King, and his aſſiſtance, may not bee compared with, or preferred before it. The whole Palati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, with the Electorall dignity, and all the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewes therereof (eſpecially in the eſtate that now it is, where there is nothing beautifull or ſolid in it,) cannot be ſo profitable, either to the King, or the Electour his Nephew, as at this time, that ſole Friendſhip of the King, ſitting ſtill, and carrying himſelfe as a neutrall, is to the Auſtrians.</p>
            <p>As the puiſſance of no King, Prince, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire in the world at this day, can bee compared with that, by which the moſt Glorious King of Great Brittaine at this time excells and exceeds others; ſo there is none which is ſo formidable and more to bee feared than that is, which is alike fatall to the Auſtrians and Spaniards. The Kings of England, from time to time have beene very powerfull, and for their commodious Sci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuation of the Iland, and their command of the Sea have beene ever to bee feared. But none of them did ever attaine to that height of power, to which King <hi>Charles</hi> hath now aſcended: who with one breath rules and governes three, the moſt powerfull, flouriſhing, and populous king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes, abounding, in the ſuperlative degree, with all things neceſſary for peace and warre; and (which is the chiefeſt, and of moſt importance)
<pb facs="tcp:2838:55"/>
hem'd in with two great Ilands, not without great difficulty to be entred: who with an unconquered, and continuall Navy, is Admirall of the Sea, and by moſt ſtrong Garriſons keepeth the channell, and as hee thinketh fitting, right, and neceſſary, doth either open or ſhut it as his pleaſure: who hath aſſigned certaine annuall and continuall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venewes and profits, to mainetaine a Navy, and now and then to repaire it with new ſupplies: at whoſe becke and will (if hee pleaſe to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand, and uſe them) all the Navies in the Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Ocean, in both the Balticke-ſeas, in Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke, about the coaſts of the Neatherlands, and Sweden, are ready, and will hoyſe up ſailes: who enjoyes a moſt firme peace, and encompaſſed about with a numerous Of ſpring, reply &amp; reſts upon many proppes, and ſtaies: who goevrnes a moſt obedient people, that accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome themſelves to obſerve his commands with a willing minde; who hath the command of a moſt warlike Nation, and moſt valiant in their undertakings of Armes both by Sea and Land: who hath in a readineſſe ſome Myriades of moſt skilfull Marriners, &amp; approved Pilots; who is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther terrified by feare or ſuſpition of ſedition, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacy, or diſobedience, nor yet diſturbed in His purpoſes, and intentions: who ſafely, and that with his great advantuge, may invade his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; but cannot bee invaded without danger to the attempters: who can wage warre againſt
<pb facs="tcp:2838:55"/>
other Princes, with profit, and without danger; and prevent and ſuppreſſe, in the very beginning a warre that is made againſt him, before it comes neare him: But, as he is moſt obſervant of his covenants, and moſt deſirous of peace, and the greateſt lover of juſtice, and equity: So doth he alſo deſire no other mans right, provoketh no man unadviſedly, but onely endeavoureth to keepe and maintaine that which is his owne. For, ſuch is the juſtice, piety, and integrity of this great Monarch, (for hee hath theſe graces, which are the ſupporters of his royall throne, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt others, proper and engraffed in his royall breaſt) that, he will keepe his covenants, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and leagues, that are made with him, whether of peace or commerce, wholly, punctu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and inviolably with all men; and not take up Armes for profit, and by violence; but with neceſſity, and mature preparation; preferring the ſecurity and ſafety of his people, before his owne private revenge or deſires.</p>
            <p>That the Spaniards, at this day, keepe poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Flanders and the Netherlands; that they have free ingreſſe, and egreſſe, to their owne ſhores, bayes, and havens; that they can trade and traffique with their ſo far diſtant and remote Kingdomes; that they can ſend their money, by letters of exchange, to maintaine their Armies; that they can take up, and bring freſh ſouldiers and ſupplies into the field: All this, is by the favour of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:56"/>
King <hi>Charles:</hi> For had it pleaſed him, at that time, when the French and Hollanders, with their joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned forces and Armies marched into Flanders, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to have given them a ſmall aſſiſtance, or have reached out his hand to the common prey; there is no man doubts, but they had beene turned out of the Netherlands, and beene beaten by Sea, and enforced to retire into their ancient Caves and Dens beyond the Pyrenean mountains.</p>
            <p>Hence then it is manifeſt, how needfull and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoovefull it is, for the Spaniards and the Auſtrians, to have for a friend (or at the leaſt no enemy, but a mediatour both of Peace and Warre) ſo potent a Commander of the Sea. They ought therefore carefully to take heed, that they doe not alienate or eſtrange Him from them; that they move Him not to wrath, diſpleaſe Him, or ſtirre Him up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt them. For if they ſhould have the King their Foe, and Enemy (the trueth is) they would ſoone be reduced to order, and forbeare their pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laging and invaſion of other Kingdomes and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pires; and be compelled to alter their purpoſe of an univerſall Monarchie throughout <hi>Europe,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſcarce ſafe in their owne houſes and countrey; and altogether unable to maintaine themſelves. If the King would, but at the leaſt, prohibite, and hinder them from comming upon the Seas, from uſing of traffique and navigation; their power and ſtrength would ſoone come to a ſtraight: For He might, if He thought fit to undertake it, in a ſhort
<pb facs="tcp:2838:56"/>
ſpace of time, and within one yeere, chaſe them off from the Ocean, like that great <hi>Pompey,</hi> who with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the ſpace of three yeeres, ſcoured the Sea of all Pirates through the whole Roman Empire. If any one doe well conſider the particulars, he ſhall have cauſe enough to deteſt, either the impudence, or obſtinacy, or arrogance of the Auſtrians and Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards; in that, in the Palatine Cauſe, they have not onely, not given ſatisfaction to the moſt reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and iuſt demands of ſo mighty a King; (whoſe Peace affords them ſafeguard and ſecurity) but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo that they ſtill hinder His Nephews from being reſtored to the former ſtate of their Dignity and fortune. But let them know, That, as anger in he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roick ſpirits is ſlow and tardy in the beginning, ſo it is fell and vehement, if being overmuch provoked it ſhall move it ſelfe with a juſt violence. <hi>Philip &amp; Peucer. in Chronic. Carion.</hi> At length (without doubt) the juſt Nemeſis will awake, and riſe againſt them, requiring vengeance and puniſhment of thoſe arrogant oppreſſors of the innocent, and pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lagers both of Kingdomes and Provinces.</p>
            <p>Now if <hi>Caeſars</hi> propoſitions be looked upon, as they are attired in the veſtments of the annexed Conditions; they are to be reputed ſtill viler, baſer and more opprobrious. I pray you, what favour is this, which tends to trouble &amp; diſgrace, &amp; withall, is to be bought at ſo deare a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ate? Briefly, every man may ſee, that this is intended chiefly, That both the moſt Illuſtrious Palatine family, moſt ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervant
<pb facs="tcp:2838:57"/>
of their liberty, and the ancient Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, may be utterly oppreſſed, and continue in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall infamy, that it riſe not againe; and that their friends and abettors may be circumvented and hindred from taking of Armes; and that they may not, upon the occaſions and moments of time apprehended, aſſociate themſelves with the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enemies of the Auſtrians.</p>
            <p>Laſtly; it muſt be given you to underſtand, that The Emperour, in his laſt anſwere, which he did likewiſe in the former, preſſed the Ambaſſador, to deſcend to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars; and more plainely, either by writing, or, if it pleaſed him, (which his Imperiall Majeſty did judge more convenient) by vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call conference, with his Imperiall Majeſties Commiſsioners, to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine what the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Britaine doth offer, and intend to performe, to His Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, in exchange of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:57"/>
theſe faire offers; that each Party proceeding in a faire equipage, (as the cuſtome is) it may be treated, agreed, and concluded concerning the Propoſitions demanded; and the Conditions to bee performed on both ſides: which His Sacred Imperiall Majeſty thought con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentany and agreeable to reaſon.</p>
            <p>But the Ambaſſador in his propoſition, and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terward, declared, That his King, if for His ſake there ſhould be a reſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, not onely of one part, but of the whole Palatinate, with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorate; and ſo the foundation of an univerſall peace ſhould be laid: Then Hee would make a league with the Emperour, and the whole Houſe of Auſtria, and the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:58"/>
Princes of the Empire, to begin, ſetle, and continue a peace.</p>
            <p>A very good, and moſt faire requitall! who could hope, and expect more? The King offered more than enough; and yet the Caeſareans, and Spaniards, were not contented with it: They would have, that the Ambaſſadour ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrate, and ſhew in particulars, with what couenants and conditions, the King of great Brit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine, would make his league, with the Houſe of Auſtria (for of the Empire, and the Princes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, they made no mention, nor did they much care for it; becauſe the Auſtrians ſhould get no great advantage, by ſuch a conditioned league with the Princes) or what, or how much aſſiſtance, either of Armes, money, or ſhipping, Hee did intend to covenant, and performe. But the Ambaſſadour, as a wiſe, and circumſpect man, thought it nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther reaſonable, juſt, nor honeſt, to goe further, in anſwere of things particularly, before the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour would come nearer to his demandes, and plainely declare, whether hee would conſent to the whole, and intire reſtitution, as it was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; or at leaſt, what part, and upon what tearmes, he determined to reſtore, giving hope, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, that the remainder likewiſe in ſhort time ſhould be ſurrendred.</p>
            <p>Thoſe offers, which were made and propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the name of the King, were not onely ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable
<pb facs="tcp:2838:58"/>
excellent, and beſeeming ſuch a magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimous King, moſt deſirous of the publike peace; but alſo moſt neceſſary for ſetling a peace in the whole Empire: to this adde that, the King (not bound thereunto by any obligation) offered theſe things meerely, in teſtimony of his good affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. But thoſe propoſitions obtruded and thruſt, as it were, upon the King, by the Emperour, are uncertaine, diſhonourable, unworthy, imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: ſuch as are neither anſwerable to the Kings demands, expectation and merits; and ſuch as are not expreſſions of a generous and free ſpirit, but teſtimonies of a tenacious, covetous, and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>did diſpoſition. To paſſe by that, the <hi>Caeſarean</hi> Majeſty, both in reſpect of the innocency of the Princes, that are to bee reſtored, in reſpect of the juſtice of the cauſe, and in reſpect of the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like good; that would have enſued, was obliged to farre greater conditions, namely, to the intire reſtitution of the Electorall dignity, and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions.</p>
            <p>And yet, if hee had come ſomewhat neerer to the juſt, reaſonable, and ſo often iterated de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands of the Ambaſſadour, and had paſſed over thoſe ignominious conditions which he preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed to the Electour, by conſenting to an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable reſtitution, which might have beene ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, without prejudice, and with ſafety; and withall, had propounded noble, and honeſt conditions, upon which hee would have gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:2838:59"/>
a reſtitution: then the Ambaſſadour know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how much the favour, and benevolence of <hi>Caeſar</hi> would merit, had beene ready to proceede further. But the drift of the <hi>Caeſareans,</hi> was firſt to know, what they might certainely and particular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly expect from the King, whether any, and what proviſion, of Armes, money, or ſhipping hee would grant unto them: and all to this end, that if they perceived, it would not anſwere and much conduce to their purpoſes, then, it might be law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full for them to goe backe, and diſmiſſe the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour, the treaty unconcluded. Thoſe things which are objected concerning <hi>the Diſpoſitions,</hi> confirmed by the <hi>treaty of Prague,</hi> and ratified by all the Princes of the Empire, and brought in only to excuſe, and ſettle the Emperours decrees in the Palatine cauſe, do ſufficiently declare, what is to be hoped for in the integrall reſtitution of the domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and dignity. By the decrees of Prague it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth plainely, that, there were certaine private and ſecret contracts, betweene the Bavarian, and the Emperour, by vertue whereof, the Electorall dominions and dignities were not onely given, granted, and confirmed to the Duke of Bavaria, for tearme of life; but alſo to the whole face of his father <hi>William,</hi> from whom it is called the <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>helmian</hi> Line, to endure for ever: for the decree runneth in theſe words:</p>
            <p>As much as concerneth the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:59"/>
Palatin cauſe: it is enacted, that thoſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> things which His Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rial Maieſty hath determined, both concerning the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate &amp; dominions therof, in the behalfe of the moſt Illuſtrious Duke of Bavaria, and the Line of <hi>William,</hi> and otherwiſe; as alſo, what hee hath ordered, concerning the goods of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine Palatine Adminiſtrators, they ſhall abide firme, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified; yet ſo, as it ſhall bee lawfull, for the widow of <hi>Fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dericke</hi> the fourth, ſometimes, Count Palatine of the Rhine, to enioy her dowry, ſo farre, as She can make it appeare to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertaine unto Her. But for
<pb facs="tcp:2838:60"/>
the children of the proſcribed Palatine, when they ſhall ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſely have humbled them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves (as it beſeemes them) to His Caeſarean Maieſty, ſome Princely allowance ſhall bee appointed to them, not as a due, but as a favour; not that they can claime it as their Right, but as it pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedes from the grace of the Emperour.</p>
            <p>In the diſpute concerning the Septemvirate Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine, transferred, by full power, upon the Duke of Bavaria, it is often repeated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d affirmed, that the Electorate is not onely given to the Duke of Bavaria, but to the whole Line of the Bavarians; and that the Duke of Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>burg, and others, are mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaken, who conceive the Inveſtiture to be meere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly proviſionall, and for terme of life. The moſt <hi>Auguſtine</hi> Emperour (<hi>thus he writeth
<pb facs="tcp:2838:60"/>
Cap.</hi> 4. <hi>n.</hi> 24.) hath caſt the moſt juſt and deſerved thunderbolt of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the Ban, upon the rebell <hi>Frederick,</hi> and thereby de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared him to have loſt all his Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledges, Honours, Goods, and particularly, the Electorall Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, with the Dominions thereunto annexed. Secondly, that he hath adjudged the ſaid Electorate, for Felony done by <hi>Frederick,</hi> to bee devolved to himſelfe, upon mature hearing and knowledge of the Cauſe, examining withall, theaer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, allegations, and pretences of the Duke of Neuburg. Laſtly, that he being moved with moſt weighty, and juſt argument, hath by conſent, and approbation of the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:61"/>
Electors of the Empire, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion of the Pope, really, and for ever transferred the ſaid Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, together with the Priviledges thereunto annexed, unto the moſt Illuſtrious Prince, <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of Bavaria, and the whole Bavarian Family (notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Duke of Neuburgs gain-ſaying of it) by a ſolemne and wonted Inveſtiture; ſo that His E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectorall Highneſſe having taken poſſeſsion, as well of the Right, Voice, Dignity, and Electorall power; as of the Goods, Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Lands, Dominions, and other things thereunto annexed; or, as it were, admitted into the Famous Colledge of Electours, aſſociated
<pb facs="tcp:2838:61"/>
unto that Fraternall union; and in all things, publikely enjoying the Office, Right, Function, and Dignity of the former Electour Palatine; is thought worthy of, and honoured with that Title, as well by the Pope, Colledge of Cardinalls, his Imperiall Majeſty, as the Kings of France, Spain, Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, and Denmarke. With what face then, credit, or honeſty, doth the Relator write, that the Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture of the moſt Illuſtrious Duke <hi>Maximilian,</hi> concerning the Electorall dignitie, is onely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſionall, and made, but upon cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine conditions, to bee of force onely, for te<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rme of life? The Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 words">
                  <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doth convin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:62"/>
this calumny, which the Relator himſelfe (though unwilling) can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but acknowledge. <hi>Item fol.</hi> 15. <hi>cap.</hi> 5. <hi>n.</hi> 17. Hee hath freely (ſaith he) the cauſe being maturely de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liberated by the ſpace of 2. yeares, and more, the purpoſe commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicated to the Electours, the Pope aſſenting, or rather, inſtantly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring it the Princes of the ſacred Roman Empire, urging and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proving it, forraigne Kings alſo, and Dukes, (the Duke of Newburge onely excepted) earneſtly interceding for it, with the applauſe of all good men, tranſlated the Electorate upon the moſt illuſtrious, <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of Bavaria, and the <hi>whole Bavarian
<pb facs="tcp:2838:62"/>
line,</hi> the merits of his highneſſe being knowne to the whole world, his Agnation, and right from that ancient Family ſueing for it, and other, moſt weighty cauſes, moving the Emperour thereunto; as it appeareth more at large, by the Charter of his Patent, and his Letters of Inveſtiture: and a little after, <hi>n.</hi> 175 nothing is granted proviſionally, and for time of life; no title is reſerved for the Duke of Newburg and <hi>n.</hi> 182. For the Electorate Palatine, was by the meere good will and arbitrement of the Emperour (other great, and moſt juſt cauſes, moving him to it) tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ferred upon the Duke of Bavaria, and his Noble Family,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:63"/>
without reſpect, or mention of his expence in warre, and <hi>n.</hi> 184. the matter by the ſpace of two yeeres, and more, being through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſcanned, examined, and adviſed of, hee began to tranſlate it upon <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Duke of Bavaria, and his Family <hi>n.</hi> 188. that ſo (Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice dipſoſing it) the Electorall dignity, raked out of the Aſhes, againe might returne to that Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily, to which of old it did belong; though contrary to right, law, and covenants confirmed by oath it was taken from it. <hi>n.</hi> 190. of the Electorate Palatine, by reaſon of the moſt haynous crime of rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, committed and perpetrated by the proſcribed <hi>Fredericke,</hi> fully
<pb facs="tcp:2838:63"/>
devolved to him, and juſtly and lawfully tranſlated to the Duke of Bavaria and his family.</p>
            <p>But what needes many words? Have we not heard ſufficiently already, that the Emperour doth no longer deny, but openly and publikely profeſſe in the hearing of all the world, that he hath given, conferred, and by Inveſtiture delivered, the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine Septemvirate, to Duke <hi>Maximilian,</hi> and the whole Bavarian Line? This Act indeed was, not long knowne among the Commons: Before the publication of the Articles of Prague, no man ever heard of it, unleſſe, perhaps, either by divination, ſuſpition, or conjecture, he did ſmell it out. But theſe things, as all other paſſages in this buſineſſe of transferring the Electorall Dignity, were orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red and ennacted privately, and by a compact plot, as it were, in hugger-mugger, they being neither heard, nor called, without defence, and abſent whom it moſt concerned; without the privity and conſent of the chiefe Electours and Princes (except that ſome afterwards enforced with feare did not contradict them) againſt the Laws, Right, and faith given to the contrary.</p>
            <p>But how doe theſe things ſuit and agree with thoſe of the Emperour and the Duke of Bavaria? who when in the Diet at Ratisbone, he inveſted <hi>Maximilian</hi> into the Electorate, both to the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours
<pb facs="tcp:2838:64"/>
and King <hi>Iames,</hi> did religiouſly aſſure, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe and avow, engaging his inviolable faith, that hee had tranſlated and conferred the Electorall Dignitie to the Bavarian but upon certain Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as namely, without prejudice to the right of the pretenders, and no longer than for his life. For thus hee expreſſeth himſelfe in his declaration ſolemnly made to the Electours <hi>Feb.</hi> 23. <hi>An.</hi> 1623 That, the Inveſtiture, was made without prejudice of the ſonnes of the Count Palatine, and his Brethren, as alſo of the Duke <hi>Wolfgangus Willhelmus</hi> Count Palatine, and other his kinſmen, ſo that nothing was detracted from any, of his right, but that it was expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſerved, to bee decided, as ſoone as might be, either by a friendly compoſition or by law: the controverſie being decided, whatſoever was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged
<pb facs="tcp:2838:64"/>
for them, ſhould be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered them inſtantly, after the death of <hi>Maximilian</hi> the Duke of Bavaria, and the Inve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiture, thereupon, to bee granted.</p>
            <p>The Electours alſo of Saxony, and Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, acknowledged the Duke of Bavaria, but it was upon certaine conditions, and no longer than he lived: for when he died, the title was to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtored to thoſe, to whom before the Proſcription and the tranſlation of the Palatine (ſo the words runne) by reaſon of the ſimultaneous Inveſtiture, the Electorall dignitie did of right belong.</p>
            <p>The Emperour, in his letters to King <hi>Iames</hi> the 5. of <hi>March,</hi> the ſame yeare, writeth in this manner: That hee by his declaration would not in the leaſt derogate or prejudice any in their rights; but to the pretended ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Electorall Dignitie and dominions, a doore of his
<pb facs="tcp:2838:65"/>
Imperiall grace and equitie ſhould bee alwaies left open both to the children, brother, and kinſmen of the Palatine. Furthermore, that it was ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſely inſerted in the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Inveſtiture, that by a friendly treatie, or if that would not prevaile, by a ſum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marie or royall proceſſe, it ſhould be pleaded and decided what of grace might be given to the Nephewes of the King, pretending a right of ſucceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and what of equitie to the Kindred in the Dignitie and Electorall Priviledges. And the Bavarian himſelfe alſo did averre and promiſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his faith, that he would poſſeſſe the Electorate upon Condition, and no otherwiſe, and that after
<pb facs="tcp:2838:65"/>
his death it ſhould be reſtored to him, or them, to whom by Compoſition or ſentence of Iudicature it ſhould bee adjudged. As it is more largely ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed both in the Charter of the Inveſtiture, and in the foreſaid Declaration of the Emperour, as alſo in Letters of the Electour of Saxony, to the Elector of Mentz; and in the anſwere of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of Brandenburg to the Embaſſadour of Caeſar, dated at Regiomontium in Boruſſia, the 12. of <hi>May</hi> 1627. All which notwithſtanding be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing violated, and caſt by, the ſeptemvirall dignity, with the Country, by ſecret contracts and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, is granted, and conferred upon the Line of <hi>William</hi> that is, upon all the Dukes of Bavaria, and their children.</p>
            <p>In that Decree alſo made the 24. of <hi>February</hi> this yeere laſt paſt, to which the Emperour doth now and then, affirme that hee will conſtantly adhere, he hath left ſome hope of regaining the Electorall Dignity: whileſt he thus writes againe;</p>
            <p>When it ſhall come to a Treaty, concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the Electorall Dignity, and the other demands, His Majeſty will obſerve ſuch moderation, that in thoſe things which may be granted, upon reaſonable Conditions, both the moſt Illuſtrious King of Great Brittaine, may thence diſcover the good will, and affection of His Sacred Imperiall
<pb facs="tcp:2838:66"/>
Majeſty towards Him; and, the often na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Count Palatine, may apprehend, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clination of His Caeſarean Grace towards Him: <hi>And this He alſo repeated, word for word, in His Anſwere to the Engliſh Ambaſſadour, the</hi> 30. <hi>day of</hi> Iune, <hi>of the forementioned yeere.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But it is to be obſerved, that theſe words were ſpoken, and rehearſed, long after the agreement of Prague, and the tranſlation made <hi>in facto,</hi> upon the Line of <hi>William.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Quanto in pectore hanc rem meo magis voluto,</l>
               <l>Tanto mihi aegritudo auctior eſt in animo,</l>
               <l>Ad illum modum os ſublitum eſſe.</l>
            </q>
            <p>To uſe the Plantine phraſe, not onely, to all the Counts Palatines, but to all the Princes of the Empire and others, who favoured the cauſe Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tine, being perſwaded, that the proſcription, and hatred, of the Caeſareans, was onely againſt <hi>Frede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricke,</hi> and not againſt his children; and that the Electorate ſhould be reſtored to them, after the Bavarians death; and yet deceived, eſpecially the two Electous of Saxony, and Brandenburg, who were ſo cautelous of being deluded, and yet ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed leſſe care, when they ſeemed moſt carefull.</p>
            <p>But upon what ground, with what conſcience,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:66"/>
by what right, could ſuch clandeſtine, and preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall diſpoſals be done, they being unheard, and unconſulted whom it principally concerned.</p>
            <p>Yet, as ſuch grants, and diſpoſals are nullities, and unjuſt, ſo they cannot bee confirmed by the covenants of Prague, nor by the Princes. That, they were of no validity, it appeareth, by this; firſt becauſe they were concluded privately, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Bavarians, and point-blancke contrary to the fundamentall lawes of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire; for in the golden Bull, the prime, and chiefe fundamentall law, <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>&amp;</hi> 20. <hi>&amp;</hi> 24. and other conſtitutions, it is decreed particularly, That the dignity, right, power, vote, vicariate, office, and function of the Septemvirall eminency, with their Principalities, and Dominions, (by vertue where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, the ſecular Princes Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors, are knowne to have their right, and vote in the Election of a Romane King, and his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment to the Imperiall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,)
<pb facs="tcp:2838:67"/>
ſhould bee ſo conjoyned and indiviſibly united for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, that no one part of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, ought to be ſo divided, or ſeparated from the other, at any time, or may be queſtio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in judgement, or out of judgement ſeverally, or ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judged, or divided by ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, (becauſe they ought to be unſeparable) nor ſhall any lay a claime to one part, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the other: That, if by er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, or otherwiſe, ſuch a plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiffe have prevailed, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe, judgement, or ſentence, or any thing of the like returne ſhould iſſue forth againſt this conſtitution, or otherwiſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:67"/>
to be accepted, all that which is already done, and all the conſequents, and things thence ſucceeding, ſhall be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely void in Law. Againe, in the royall Capitulation, which is the ſecond fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>damentall Law of the Romane Empire, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining, the articles, and covenants, which the Electours by way of contract, have made with the Emperour, to the religious obſervation whereof, by giving a ſolemne oath he muſt binde himſelfe, theſe things, amongſt others, are vow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and promiſed by his Imperiall Majeſty.</p>
            <p>That, in the greater cauſes concerning the Empire, hee would aske advice, and give eare to the votes, and opinions of the Electours, and decree, and confirme nothing, without their foregoing lawfull know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and conſent. That, Hee
<pb facs="tcp:2838:68"/>
would authoriſe no mandate, reſcript, or what ever elſe might bee grievous to others, againſt the golden Bull, and other conſtitutions, and cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of the Empire, nor would either himſelfe make uſe of any ſuch inſtrument, or ſuffer, that any one, ſhould purchaſe the like, or make uſe thereof. Alſo, that if hee have any controverſie, or ſuite againſt any of the Princes, he ſhall try it by law, but uſe no violence againſt them; eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially, who are willing to ſtand, to a lawfull hearing. Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, that hee will obſerve, and hinder, and neither by any
<pb facs="tcp:2838:68"/>
meanes nor upon any pretence, grant, that any of the Peeres, and States, whether an Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, Prince, or other, may be proſcribed, condemned, and declared outlaw'd, but he will endeavour, that, it may bee proceeded thereon, according to the ordinary rule of Law, and the conſtitutions of the Empire, by the preſcript of the reformed chamber of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances. A clauſe is added in the end. That if any thing ſhould bee undertaken and done contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to this, and other heads of the Capitulation, it ought to ſtand as a nullity, to bee void and of no validity.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:69"/>Let all thoſe things be conſidered, and exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, which hitherto have beene ordered, diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and done, <hi>de facto,</hi> in the Palatine cauſe, and decreed againſt him, from the beginning to this day, and thoſe eſpecially, which concernes the diſtribution of the Electorate, and diviſion of the Palatine Territories. Are not all, and each of them directly contrary to the golden Bull, and the plaine preſcript of the Capitulation, and laws? Is not the Electorall Palatinate torne in pieces, devided, and diſtracted, the greater part, together with the office, being given to the Bavarian; an other part to the Spaniard; the reſt ro others, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly againſt the prohibition? Where, whether, and when, were the Electours called, aſſembled, conſulted, and gave their votes, according to the cuſtome of their Anceſtours, while theſe things were done? Did not the Saxon, and Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burger conſtantly, and eagerly oppoſe the King <hi>Frederickes</hi> proſcription, the tranſlation of the Electorate upon the Bavarian, and the excluſion of the Kings children, and kinſmen from their right? Let the ſuffrages (given up in the Senate of Princes) in <hi>February, anno</hi> 1623. Let ſundry of their letters, to the Emperour, and their anſwers, given to the Imperiall Ambaſſadours be read. If they are now ſilent, it is becauſe they are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by violence, and feare. When the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate was tranſlated, to the Line of <hi>William</hi> the Bavarian, when thoſe conſtitutions, were forged,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:69"/>
and anvil'd in a darke ſhop, when the pacification betwixt Caeſar, and the Saxon, was to be patched up by Ambaſſadors, at Prague, where then were the other Electors and States? Did they then come in? Were they then preſent? Did they then give in their Votes, according to the cuſtome of their Anceſtours? Did their lawfull conſent, and Votes, precede it? Were they who were deprived of the Electorate, their Right and States? Were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, (who were alſo intereſſed,) cited, heard, and defended? Was this great negotiation determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, upon the hearing of the Cauſe, and according to the preſcribed Lawe? No ſuch thing was thought of, no ſuch thing done, but the cogni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zance of the Electours, States, and unſuſpected Peeres, was neglected, and rejected; and all things determined, by arbitrement, by affection, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, and fulneſſe of power; againſt juſtice, the Lawes, and Cuſtomes; the Royall Decrees, Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants, and Capitulations, againſt the cuſtomary, and due manner of proceeding; againſt the abſent, unheard, unaccuſed, guiltleſſe, plaine innocents: not in a publike aſſembly, but privately, in a cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and by a ſecret Party, theſe things were done, ſpoken, decreed written and perfected.</p>
            <p>Hence, the Electors of Saxony &amp; Brandenburg, not without cauſe, objected to the Emperour, as by way of exprobration, That in a matter ſo waighty, and of ſuch moment, whereon the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:70"/>
ſafety, or ruine of the Sacred Roman Empire (as experience will witneſſe) might depend, they were not called to Counſell, and heard, according to the Rule of Capitulation, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, when there was a controverſie, about an Electour, a principall member of the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire: That this buſineſſe, concerned one of the Septemvirate, and the Electorall Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; and therefore the Electours were not to be excluded from the cognizance thereof. That it is ſufficiently knowne, that the caſe and queſtion betwixt the Lord, and his Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall, when it is controverted about the loſſe of a Fee, according to the common feodall Law, is to be decided, and judged by the Peeres of the Court, who are of equall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, and eſtimation with the defendant, That, this Ordinance ought to bee better obſerved, when any thing is to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termined againſt them, who are now Illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrious, and eminent: That by the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of Capitulation, thoſe who are moſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timate, and familiar Counſellers to His Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarean Majeſty, and who might equalize
<pb facs="tcp:2838:70"/>
(him, that was to be puniſhed, or deprived of His Priviledges) in State, Dignity, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, ſhould have beene called to Counſell: That they did openly, and to the face of the world, proteſt; that this proſcription, and the execution thereof, was decreed, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated without their counſell, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent: That an other manner of proceeding ſhould have been obſerved, in this buſineſſe: That in the foreſaid Capitulation, it is moſt plainely ordered, and decreed, that no Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour, or other Prince of the Empire, may, without a full hearing, and ordinary proces, and judgement, be proſcribed by the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, and proclaimed an Outlaw: That they underſtood not, by what law, and pretence, the Electors could bee excluded from advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, and underſtanding a matter of ſuch weight, as might turne the Scale of the ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, or deſtruction of the Empire. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that the forme of a judiciall proceſſe, is one part of juſtice, which cannot be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred better, than by the authorized, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed Lawes, it ought to have been endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured;
<pb facs="tcp:2838:71"/>
That the Count Palatine, might have been heard before His condemnation, according to the ſtrict rule of the Law, and and the ſacred Capitulation; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore an ordinary proceſſe ſhould have beene iſſued out, according to the Conſtitutions of the Imperiall Chamber, and many other cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances have beene conſidered, before the ſentence of Proſcription had beene pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulgated: And this the rather, in reſpect of the Count Palatines Children, Brethren, and neere kinſmen; all and each whereof, are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſed of no crime, much leſſe convicted. That the tranſlation of the Electorate, and the Dominions thereunto annexed, are of no leſſe conſequence, and prejudice, than the Proſcription; and therefore of Right, they ought to have beene adviſed and conſulted withall, in that point, according to the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree of the Capitulation, and not to enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a bare intimation thereof, after it was done: That the Septemvirate, and Princes of the Empire, are under His Imperiall Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, but withall, Electors, and States of the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:71"/>
Empire, and the very pillars, and props there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of; and therefore, it is not to be queſtioned, but that the examination of this matter, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertained to them: That Caeſar would not grant, and conveigh an Imperiall Fee, or Towne, without their advice, and conſent: How much more needfull was it, that Hee ſhould have their Counſell, and approbation, when the queſtion was made about the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Electorall Dignity, and ſuch noble, and Princely Fees of the Empire? That by this proceſſe, the other Electours, Princes, and States, might receive a great, and irrecoverable loſſe, if themſelves unheard, and the Electours not called to Counſell, they, their children, and neere kinſmen, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out examination of the cauſe, might be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived, and ſpoiled of their ſtates and digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties entayled upon them, and all theſe tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to ſtrangers, by arbitrement. That by this meanes, an Electour, or Prince of the Empire, would be of a more unhappy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, than any ordinary noble perſonage of Poland, becauſe, that he cannot be proſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:72"/>
but in a full Parliament. That the eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, and prerogative, by which the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors have beene hitherto, of eminent note, within, and without the Empire, would grow of ſmall account, and that they, who formerly, in their preſence durſt not put on their hatts, might hereafter make a queſtion, whether, they ought to ſtand uncovered be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them. If the Electours ought not to be conſulted with, and know, when any Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctour is to be proſcribed, that then indeed, they could not underſtand in what the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, and authority of the Electors doth conſiſt, or (the name onely excepted) what difference there can be, betwixt them, and the minor Princes of the Empire; nor, how they may be ſecured from the danger, and prejudice to which themſelves might be ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able by this manner of proceeding; that the proſcription of the Prince, with the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing execution, and the enſuing tranſlation of the Electorate, (which ought not to have been without their advice, counſell, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent) was done without their knowledge;
<pb facs="tcp:2838:72"/>
that the Electors, and Princes ought not to be of a more unhappy condition, eſpecially in regard of condemnation, and puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, than the meaneſt ſort of men, againſt whom, unheard, and uncited, there can bee no proceeding, or ſentence of condemnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on pronounced, though their crimes be moſt notorious.</p>
            <p>All theſe arguments, which wee have touched by way of Collection, following the heads of things, and but a reliſh of; both thoſe Electors, of moſt renowned and eminent authority and eſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation; who out of their owne knowledge, have teſtified, and in their publike writings, and letters; in their ſpeeches in open Parliament; by moſt ample Embaſſies; have very often, and more than ſufficiently written and declared. And it is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parent from thoſe things, though but related, upon what foundation of trueth, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit, thoſe things are built, which were formerly urged out of the Author <hi>De Septemviratu in Ducem Bavariae optimo jure tranſlato;</hi> and what is to bee thought of the tranſlation of the Electorate; done ſo privately, without the required ſolemnities, and the lawfull advice of the Electors aſſembled. But of this argument, there will be a more convenient place, to ſpeake hereafter. It ſhall now ſuffice, to bring in this concluſion, out of thoſe premiſes;
<pb facs="tcp:2838:73"/>
that all thoſe Diſpoſitions, Decrees, Covenants, Sentences and Executions, are of no force in Law, but void, unjuſt, and of no conſequence, or effect; as the Law, and Iuſtice doe pronounce them. <hi>l. Si expreſſe</hi> 19. <hi>D. de appellationibus &amp; relationibus.</hi> where it is ſaid, <hi>That the ſentence is not to be pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced if it be made directly againſt the Lawes or a Decree of the Senate, or Conſtitution.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore, if any man ſhall appeale from ſuch ſentence and be diſcharged by decree, the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence is made of no force by that ordinance. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>de regul in</hi> 6. <hi>l. ex ſtipendatione. l. probatam a praeſide. c. de ſont, &amp; inte locut, Novel</hi> 113.</p>
            <p>And againe, it is to be obſerved, that the agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and covenants of private men, cannot de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate from the publike right, the lawes, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of the Common-weale. <hi>l. nec ex praetorio, nec ex ſolemni jure privatorum conventione quicquam immutandum eſt.</hi> 27. <hi>&amp; l. neque pignus. § privatorum conventio jur publico non derogat. F. de regulis juris. l. juris gentium.</hi> 7. §. 16. <hi>ibi. pactum a iure communi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motum ſervari non oportet. &amp; l. contra iuris civilis regulas pacta conventa rata non habentur.</hi> 28. <hi>&amp; l. ius publicum privatorum pactis mutari non poteſt.</hi> 55. <hi>D. de Adminiſtr. rerum ad civitat. l. nemo poteſt.</hi> 55. <hi>D. de le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gat.</hi> 1. <hi>l. pacta quae contra leges conſtitutioneſque vel contra bonos mores ſiunt nullam vim habere indubitati juris eſt.</hi> 6. <hi>c. de pactis.</hi> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re, <hi>no reſcript of Caeſars, no royall decree, no ſacred obſervation, which appeare contrary to the generall rule of the law, are of any validi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:73"/>
nor may be produced as proofes in a controverſie, thus the Emperour Anaſtatius hath decreed, l. ultima c. ſi contra jus vel utilitatem publicam.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, thoſe diſpoſitions were concluded againſt faith, and caution given; meerely to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive them, to whom the promiſe was made, as is aboveſaid; where it is ſhewed that Caeſar, and the Bavarian Lad religiouſly and often promiſed, and warranted, that the Electorall dignitie, was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon <hi>Maximilian</hi> alone, and to him too, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, for tearme of life, and that, after his death, the children, and kindred of King <hi>Fredericke,</hi> were againe to be admitted. Moreover, they whom it concerned, and which were grieved, were not called, and impleaded, as wee have heard; for in acts that may bee prejudiciall, all whom it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes ought to bee cited. For ſo <hi>Divus Marcus l.</hi> 39. <hi>ibi. They alſo being preſent, that would oppoſe the decree, that is, might bee grieved by the ratification. D. de adoption.</hi> where <hi>Gothofredus</hi> giveth this rule, <hi>Hee is alwayes to be cited that may bee injured. l.</hi> 47. <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in every matter ought to be given they being preſent, whom the matter concernes. D. de rejudicat. l. etiamſi Patre.</hi> 29.9. <hi>ſi haere litate Patris.</hi> 2. <hi>ibi. non evocatis creditoribus minime id praeiudicaſſe. D. de minoribus Ioachimus a Beuſt. in l. admonendi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n.</hi> 796. <hi>D. de jureju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rando B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t, whatſoever is ordered, decreed, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>one, and concluded againſt the abſent is nothing l. ſi ut proponis.</hi> 5. <hi>ibi. What is ſo carried againſt thee, in thy abſen e, ought not to be referred to the effect of the law. &amp; l. ea
<pb facs="tcp:2838:74"/>
quae ſtatuuntur adverſus abſentes. c. Quomodo &amp; quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do Index ſentent. When,</hi> ſaith <hi>Symmachus,</hi> in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine epiſtle, <hi>did things concluded of amongſt others, wrong thoſe which were abſent and ignorant? L.</hi> 1. <hi>ibi. It is often decreed, That matters paſſed in private for the one partie, can doe no prejudice to the other.</hi> And <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>ibi. This law is notoriouſly knowne, that a tranſaction made amongst ſome in private cannot prejudice the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, &amp; ibi. For neither, though they have made a divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in thy abſence can it derogate from thy right. c. In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter alios acta, aliis non noceret. argt. l. tranſact. matris.</hi> 26. <hi>c. de tranſact. &amp; l. Imp.</hi> 3. <hi>ibi. Privatis pactionibus non dubium eſt non laedi jus caeterorum. D. eodem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Laſtly, all theſe acts were drawne up, againſt ſuch as were then in their Minoritie, undefended, unheard, fatherleſſe Orphans, and whoſe title came by atchievement. For when thoſe contracts betweene the Bavarian and Caeſar were made, and the Covenants of Prague were peeced, <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> was yet as a ward as the reſt of his bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren are at this preſent day. He alone had then attained the age of 18. yeeres, the time preſcribed by the Golden Bull, for the full age of the Electors children. But the Emperours affirme, that what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is decreed againſt an Orphane, he is unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fended, &amp; under protection of a Guardian it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endamage him at his riper yeeres. 1. <hi>acta apud ſe.</hi> 45. §. <hi>contra indefenſos minores nulla ſententia pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferenda eſt.</hi> 3. <hi>&amp; l. contra pupillum indeſenſum, vel mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem xxv. annis, propoſitum nihil momenti habet,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:74"/>
which in Engliſh runneth thus, <hi>Againſt Orphans undefended, or under the age of</hi> 25. <hi>yeeres, a peremptory ſentence is of no validitie.</hi> 54 <hi>D. de reiudicata. No man,</hi> (to uſe the Civilians Language) <hi>can bee deprived of an atchieved right, no, not by Caeſar uſing all his royall prerogative.</hi> To take any thing from another vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, is more againſt nature, than Death, than paine, than povertie, or what elſe may happen to the eſtate of the body, or of Fortune. <hi>Cicer. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>Offic.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But concerning the confirmation, and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation of thoſe Diſpoſals, it is to be underſtood.</p>
            <p>Firſt, that a contract againſt the allowed cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, lawes and liberties, is a nullitie, nor can be confirmed, ratified, or allowed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that the approving thereof by the ſtates (which is yet uncertaine, whether ſo or no) is unlawfull, and of no validitie; becauſe they were not preſent, nor called, and aſſembled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, that the cauſe being firſt heard, they might then give their conſents: and if any did ſo, and ſuffragated to Caeſars propoſitions, they did it ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verally, and apart, which by law ought not to bee done. <hi>l. item ſi unut.</hi> 17. § <hi>item ſi plures.</hi> 2. <hi>and l non diſtinguemns.</hi> 32. §. <hi>Cum in plures. ibi. Non deb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulos ſeparatim coge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e. D. de receptis qui arbitrium. c. cum omnes. Extra. de conſit. de conſtit. Hieronym. a Cavellis in ſpicul. Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1+ letters">
                     <desc>•…</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>un opin. quaest.</hi> 476. <hi>Anton. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber. in Cod. Deciſion. foren. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 3. <hi>definit.</hi> 42. where he ſheweth, that <hi>It is not to be reputed a generall Act,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:75"/>
which is done by particular perſons, though done by all, if they be not aſſembled into one Company.</hi> and <hi>Flamin. de Rubeis conſil.</hi> 69. <hi>n.</hi> 220. <hi>lib.</hi> 1. ſaith, <hi>the Record is of no power though all the parties conſent, if they agree ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally, and the ſeverall perſons are not lawfully congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gated.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, moſt of the Princes, eſpecially the Proteſtants which aſſented to the treaty of Prague, were enforced thereunto, and conſtrai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by feare, menaces, armes and peremptorie Commands to approve it, if not they had bin pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claimed open enemies, as it is expreſſed in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſter: but the law teacheth what ought to bee thought of ſuch conſents, and allowance. <hi>See l. velle non creditur. D. de regulis iuris. and there Deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um, &amp; Dol. ibi. Neceſsitas impoſita contraria volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tati. D. quod metus cauſa. Cuiac. obſerv. ult. lib.</hi> 16. Whatſoever is extorted and done by feare; is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted as nothing, and cannot bee ratified. <hi>D. Quod metus cauſa. l. ſi donationis.</hi> 7. <hi>and l. ult. c. de his quae vi metuſve cauſa geſta ſunt. where it is concluded, ratum haberi non patietur &amp; quae per potentiam extor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta ſunt, praecipimus infirmari,</hi> in Engliſh thus, <hi>it muſt not be permitted, that ſuch a concluſion may bee ratified, and we command, that whatſoever is wreſted away vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, ſhall not be authorized. Bartol in lib.</hi> 1. §. <hi>quae veneranda in ſin. D. Quarum rerum actio non. datur, &amp; de except. iuriſiurand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In fine, it is not to bee ſaid, and concluded in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly, that all they, which complyed themſelves
<pb facs="tcp:2838:75"/>
to the treaty of Prague, did allow, and ratifie all, and the ſeverall articles in that ſenſe, as it is there expreſſed, and in particular thoſe Diſpoſals of the Palatine Electorate, there mentioned, they being ſuch, as never came to their knowledge. Surely ſome, and amongſt them the Elector of Branden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burg, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſented with an expreſſe reſervation, &amp; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, either generall <hi>ſalvo uniuſcuiuſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> iure,</hi> ſaving every mans right, or ſpecialty as the ſame Elector hath done in this Palatine cauſe. And the reſt are thought to have ſubſcribed under the ſame ſecret condition: For this clauſe, <hi>Salvo iure tertii,</hi> though it be omitted, is alwayes notwithſtanding concei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to be included in the writings. <hi>d. l ult. c. ſi con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traius vel utilitat. public.</hi> 1. <hi>ſi quando § ult. x. de reſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis c. ſuper eo. x. de crim. falſ.</hi> For none of them would ſeeme ſo uniuſt and partiall, knowingly to confirme an uniuſt thing, and a nullitie, by their conſent, and require, that he ſhould be deprived of his right, whom they were perſwaded, and knew to be an Innocent and much wronged. Nor is it ſufficient, to ſay, that thoſe Diſpoſals were confirmed by the Princes of the Empire, unleſſe that alſo it be openly ſhewed, that the confirma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made with knowledge of the cauſe. For, this is neceſſary, ſaith <hi>Nicolaus Burgundus</hi> in his booke of the Bavarian Electorate, written in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenſe of <hi>Chriſtophorus Gewoldus, fol.</hi> 284. that any one may be thruſt out of his poſſeſſion; nor doth a light, curſorie, and perfunctorie underſtanding of the cauſe ſuffice. A full and exact knowledge
<pb facs="tcp:2838:76"/>
is required, <hi>allegat. Iaſon. ad l. iudices. n.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp;</hi> 3. <hi>c. de iudic. Decius ad l. non videtur. § qui iuſsit. D. de. reg. juris.</hi> And this kind is not preſuppoſed, but is to be prooved by lawfull witneſſes, or ought to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare out of the Acts, as the ſame <hi>Burgundus</hi> in the ſame place affirmeth, adding <hi>Panor. ad c.</hi> 2. <hi>n.</hi> 8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 22. <hi>de ſequeſt. poſſeſ. Alciat. de praeſump regul.</hi> 2. <hi>praeſum.</hi> 9. <hi>Menochius remed. recuper.</hi> 8. <hi>n.</hi> 26. <hi>&amp;</hi> 27. <hi>&amp;</hi> 15. <hi>n.</hi> 405. <hi>&amp; lib.</hi> 2. <hi>praeſumpt.</hi> 67. <hi>n.</hi> 12. 13. <hi>&amp; praeſumpt.</hi> 75 <hi>n.</hi> 22. <hi>l. judices. c.</hi> 6. <hi>de iudiciis deſumpta ex codice Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doſian. lib.</hi> 2. <hi>c.</hi> 18. <hi>ibid. inprimis rei qualitatem plena inquiſtione diſcutere c. iudicantem.</hi> 31. <hi>queſt.</hi> 8. I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beare to proſecute, and bring to light the other Nullities, and acts of violence and injuſtice, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in framing thoſe diſpoſals, and the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants of Prague, for tranſlation of the Electorate.</p>
            <p>I ſhall here, only by way of imitation, tranſcribe ſome things making for this purpoſe, out of that book formerly quoted, which <hi>Nicolaus Burgundus,</hi> a Lawyer, Bavarian Advocate, and Profeſſor in the Vniverſity of <hi>Ingolſtad,</hi> wrote concerning the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varian Septemvirate, otherwiſe called the Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie for <hi>Chriſtopher Gewoldus.</hi> For what was lawfull for him to ſpeake and thinke, of the Decree of <hi>Charles</hi> the 4th. by which it is declared, and ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, That the Electorate ſhould be annexed to the Countie Palatine of the Rhyne, and not belong to the Bavarians: That we may ſpeake, and conclude more truly, and juſtly, of thoſe new, clandeſtine, and irregular Decrees of <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſecond, and the Treaty of Prague.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:2838:76"/>Wilt thou (<hi>ſaith he fol.</hi> 78) have this ſtand for the ſentence of a Iudge? It can not be called ſo, where nothing is done orderly and legally. Ought not a Court to be called, and the caſe pleaded, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſentence ſhould be given? Here was no exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, here was no controverſie at all. The examination begins with the Citation, if the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary be not called, there is no examination: Where there hath been no examination, there is no ſentence. Who ever warned <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> and His brethren to appeare in Law? It is appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, they were not preſent, therefore the ſentence <hi>fol.</hi> 79. is utterly voyd, becauſe it was pronounced, the Adverſaries being neither cited, nor heard, <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>&amp; ibid. Bald. c. ſi. per vim. vel alio modo l.</hi> 1. 5. <hi>item cum ex edicto. D. de ſentent. quae ſine appellat reſcind.</hi> And conſequently, by that ſentence, no man can be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived of his right. <hi>c.</hi> 1. <hi>defeud. ſine culpa non amittend. Anchor. conf.</hi> 33. <hi>vol.</hi> 1.</p>
            <p>Perhaps, you will ſay, It was lawfull for the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, <hi>ex officio,</hi> to enquire for the trueth: It is done uſually in caſes criminall, but not uſed in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate buſineſſes. And yet by ſuch inquiry, he could not condemne the Palatines, without a lawfull Citation; becauſe, an hurtfull teſtimony is not to be credited, the party not being heard, <hi>elem. Paſtor. de rejudicat. Roman. conſil.</hi> 245. Many things, indeed are required, before the abſent can be condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and thruſt from his poſſeſſion. He is firſt to be impleaded at the Law, the Decree is to be pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed, and he to be declared contumacious: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe,
<pb facs="tcp:2838:77"/>
by the Lawes, Cuſtomes, and Ordinances of our Anceſtours, it is not rightly brought to ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, though the Emperour himſelfe adjudge it. <hi>d. elem. Paſtoral. Abbas ad c.</hi> 1. <hi>de cauſ propriat &amp; poſſeſ. Baldus ad l. ultim. de legib.</hi> If you ſhall ſpeake of a Prerogative <hi>fol.</hi> 83. you ought to know, that the Emperour, with all his authority, cannot by his Prerogative, take away any mans proper right, without a juſt and publike cauſe. What was the juſt cauſe, that the Electorate ſhould be violently plucked away from the Palatines? None. What was the publike cauſe? None. The whole ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation, tended particularly for the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Bavarians. The whole Scene was made and laid meerely for their advantage. What remaines therefore, but that we may call that prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative a nullity, which doth tend to the injury of the Palatines; which contrary to the rule of the Law, doth ſnatch away the Palatines right, and thruſt them from their poſſeſſion? But you will ſay, <hi>fol.</hi> 94. the Emperour and the Electours, and the States of the Empire, have confirmed it. I grant it. But what is the power of a confirmation? If we beleeve thoſe who are learned in the Law, it confirreth no new Title, but only ſtrengtheneth that which is already given, <hi>Molinaeus ad conſuet. Pariſi. titulo.</hi> 1. §. 8. <hi>gloſſ.</hi> 1. <hi>n.</hi> 88. and implies withall, this condition, <hi>If the caſe be thus; Molinaeus loco <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tat. Rebuff. tractat. de decim.</hi> 13. <hi>n.</hi> 90. 91. But ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, you have no Charter, and therefore the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is vain, and frivolous. For where that which
<pb facs="tcp:2838:77"/>
is confirmed, is nothing, there the confirmation is nothing alſo: for that which is of no validity, is accounted, as if it had not been done at all <hi>l.</hi> 1. § <hi>haec autem D. quod quiſq. ius in alter. ſtat.</hi> And what is not, cannot be confirmed. Thus farre I have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in the words of <hi>Burgundus,</hi> ſave onely, that the name of the Palatines, is uſed in ſtead of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varians.</p>
            <p>But, if it be lawfull for the Bavarians, to oppoſe the diſpoſall of the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the 4th. for ſetling the Palatine Electorate, and the golden Bull, confirmed by all the Princes of the Empire, and by three ages obſerved, and eſtabliſhed, and to account it as a nullity in that behalfe, and to ſay it was wreſted, and gotten ſurreptitiouſly, and frau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulently; and made by the Emperour, in two much favour of the Palatines, and hate of the Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>varians, that he might oppreſſe them, under a ſhew of Law: Why may it not now be lawfull, for the Palatines, by the ſame ground, and reaſon, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fute, and call, by the name of a Nullity, that diſpoſition of <hi>Ferdinand,</hi> concerning the granted Electorate, to the Bavarians, and thoſe written Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venants of Prague, confirming and allowing it, made, and patched up together out of hate againſt the Palatines, whoſe oppreſſion, under colour, and pretence of Law, <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and the Bavarian did en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to haſten, that they might the more eaſily attaine to their owne ends?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Burgundus</hi> ſaies further of the Emperour <hi>Charles, fol.</hi> 63. that hee was in all things reſpective of the
<pb facs="tcp:2838:78"/>
Palatines, and diſpleaſed with the Bavarians, and therefore having excluded theſe laſt, he gave, and adjudged the Electorate to the former; what won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der? for he joyned in Armes with <hi>Rupertus</hi> the Palatine, for the ruine of the Bavarians. <hi>Henricus Rebdorff in annal.</hi> and afterwards miſerably ſpoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led all Bavaria. When therefore hee would give way to his owne deſire, while he ſought to pleaſe his owne affection, foming with a moſt burning hatred againſt the Bavarians, he greedily ſnatcheth at that occaſion, agreeing with his Genios, that hee might take vengeance of his enemies, and keepe them (unable to reſiſt him) below the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of their Anceſtours. And not much after <hi>fol.</hi> 72. theſe things being thus ordered, when the Electors were prepoſeſſed, when <hi>Rupert</hi> the Count Palatine, did flouriſh in moſt eminent grace, when the Bavarians were involved in the doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full hazard of warre; briefely, when all things were brought to that paſſe, that the Bavarians were accounted as enemies, and the Palatine ſtood as a favourite: <hi>Rupertus</hi> the Count Palatine, in the yeare 1356. in the Diet at Norinberg, obtai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned a Charter of Letters patents, by which the Electours affirme the office of Arch-Sewer, and the Electorate, to be annexed to the Countie Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latine of the Rhine. Surely, nothing at that time was more eaſie to be obtained than that. Hee had the Emperour of his party, and the Emperour drew all the Electours unto his ſentence; for they all ſubſcribed, according to the forme which
<pb facs="tcp:2838:78"/>
               <hi>Charles</hi> had preſcribed them. They had ſeverally concluded, what they ought all joyntly to have queſtioned <hi>fol.</hi> 232. You were better not ſpeake of <hi>Charles</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and his Bull: we know, we know what he intended; and now all men know, that we know it. Hee ſacrificed unto his wrath againſt all law and right, againſt the cuſtomes of our An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtours; he endeavoured to conferre the Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate upon the Palatines, whom hee loved moſt dearely, that he might ſnatch it from the Bava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians, whom he hated moſt deadly. This is that he would have, this is that hee intended, and aymed at; and how he might attaine unto this end, hee ſummoned all his wits together. Speake now <hi>fol.</hi> 298. what, as much, and as eloquently as you can; yet this is our Iewell, which <hi>Otho</hi> the third ſet into Bavaria; by him we came into poſſeſſion, and upon him we reſt. <hi>Charles</hi> the fourth labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in vaine to take it thence, what ever he did, he could effect nothing. It ſtood ſecure, and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved above the top of power, the ſupreame hand of puiſſance could not reach thither, nothing was done lawfully, nothing orderly, nothing ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnely. It was no judiciary ſentence, but vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence. He caſt out the Bavarians by extreame in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jury; that, againſt all right he might bring in the Palatines. Your beginning is wicked, the procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding unjuſt, and to conclude, the whole poſſeſſion vitious. Thus farre he.</p>
            <p>But now, as before is done, place onely the Pala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tines, and the Palatinate for the Bavarians, and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:79"/>
Bavaria; <hi>Maximilian</hi> Duke of Bavaria, for <hi>Ruper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus; Ferdinand,</hi> for <hi>Charles:</hi> the diſpoſitions of the Electorate, and the treaty of Prague, for the gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bull; the Diet of Ratisbone, for that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rimberg; you will ſay (the perſons onely being changed) the ſame play is acted at this day, which is feigned by <hi>Burgundus,</hi> to have beene acted lnog ſince, and was firſt ſhewed upon the ſtage, by <hi>Chriſtopherus Gewaldus,</hi> by an artificially contrived tale.</p>
            <p>Theſe were the firſt which ſtood up, as the chiefe patrons of the Bavarian cauſe, who have not feared to oppoſe, and accuſe of falſitie, and nullity, the ſacred, and for ſo many ages invio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late, authority of the golden Bull. But if it bee lawfull, for private men to vilefie, and make voide the moſt ſacred decrees, the wiſeſt ordinances, of our Anceſtours the continuall cuſtome obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by ſo many Ages, allowed, confirmed, and ſealed with the imprinted ſeales of the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and Electours: I will not ſay what confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, but what hope of ſetling the ſtate remaines? What can be ſafe, juſt, and inviolable in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſociety of men, in the ſucceſſion, and poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of dignities, and offices? woefull experience doth teſtifie, what miſeries have attended this oppoſall of the golden Bull, and uſurpation of the Palatine Electorate: In one word, deadly warre, cruell ſlaughter, horrid proſcriptions, and the moſt to bee lamented, diſtraction of the whole Empire, the chiefe and principall cauſe of this
<pb facs="tcp:2838:79"/>
continued, and renewed mortall warre, being, the ſnatching away of the Electorall dignity, which the moſt illuſtrious Electors, of Saxony, and Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denburg, foreſaw immediately, and foretold from the beginni g: <hi>They affirmed, that the tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Electorate, was not a meanes to ſtay the warre, but rather an occaſion which might produce, and raiſe more bitternes of mind ſchiſme and diviſion among the Princes, and the univerſall diſtraction and deſolation of the Empire; that therefore they thought it needfull, that the Count Palatine ſhould be reſtored; that a ſecure and true peace might be ſetled, that by rigour there could bee no courſe taken for the ſafety of the Republique; which by that meanes was rather drawne into danger and invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in a perpetuall warre. Againe, that they adiudged the tranſlation of the Electorate, to be the principall cauſe of theſe troubles and warre; becauſe the children of the Count Palatine, in regard of their knowne innocency, might by no meanes be excluded from their dignity, and dominions, thoſe eſpecially, who before the pretended cryme of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther had obtained the priviledges atchieved by the provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence and covenant of their forefathers in the Electorall Palatinate Beſides, that their neereſt kinſmen of blood (to whom the right of atchivement did likewiſe appertaine, by the ſimultaneous Inveſtiture) were wronged, and deprived of their right. The ſame moſt Illuſtrious Princes, have more then on e, and againe complained openly, that their good, peaceable counſels were not hearkned unto, but that thoſe meanes were undertaken, which in deede were cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of more ſtirs commotion and enmity; for experience it ſelfe plainely ſhewing that the ſtate did ſtill grow worſe, in
<pb facs="tcp:2838:80"/>
regard that thoſe courſes, (from which they had uſed all arguments of diſſwaſion, as being the ſeeds of diſcord were nevertheleſſe preferred, and put into execution with all vehemency of ſpirit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, not onely both thoſe Electours by their owne Ambaſſadours, but alſo the reſt of their col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leagues, and the other Princes which were preſent at Ratisbone, in the yeare 1623, when <hi>Caeſar</hi> was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to have confirmed the Electorall dignity up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Bavarian, by a generall conſent teſtified, that King <hi>Frederick</hi> was not the incendiary, and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chitect of the ſtirres in the Empire, themſelves af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming it, in theſe words. <hi>That the Count Palatine is a young Prince, who being ſeduced by others, knowes not how to adviſe himſelfe:</hi> and againe, <hi>that hee was not the authour and beginner of thoſe commotions in Bohemia, but that they had their beginning, and proceedings before he was ingaged therein.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, it is much to be admired at, and lamented, (that I may not ſay it is worthy of blame, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe) that the Emperour, and Electours for ſo many yeares, and in ſo many ſundry Parliaments, and in theſe two laſt kept at Ratisbone, in the yeares 1630, and 1636. neglected to hearken to the demands of the King of great Brittaine, and by the granted and decreed reſtitution of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate upon reaſonable termes, to reſtore peace to the Empire, and their Countrey, ſo ſhaken with civill diſſention, and warre. How can they excuſe it before God and men, of this preſent and the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing ages? Had they not cauſes weighty, and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent
<pb facs="tcp:2838:80"/>
enough; to move them to preferre peace before warre, that thoſe tumults being quieted, and ſome perſonages reſtored to their former eſtates and fortunes, they might ſettle themſelves, and the whole Empire, in the tranquillity, ſafety, ſecurity, and honour? Ought not, both the preſent common calamities of the Chriſtian Commonweale, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther neere approaching, ſtirre and rouſe them up? ought not the mournefull cryes, intermingled with teares, of their waſted, and deſolate Country, move them, and pricke them forward, to an intimate com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeration? They might have learned, by the events, and inſtructions of ſo many yeeres, that the ſafety, liberty, Honour, and quiet of the Commonweale, was contained in that reſtitution, and the Decree for forgetfulneſſe: but contrarily, that by the expul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and oppreſſion, of the moſt Illuſtrious Electo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Palatine Houſe; this woefull warre was not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, not extenuated and abated, but grown more grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous, and raiſed to ſuch a flame, that thereby all Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many is ſet on fire, and the neighbouring people and nations are ſcorched. What fruit hath this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuation of the warre brought forth? What profit and power hath thereby accrued to the Common-weale, it is knowne to the world: and the Victories themſelves, muſt needs confeſſe, what ſmall profit they have gotten by their victories; to wit, that they were never the more ſecure, but have received more loſſe, and trouble; more ignominie, and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, than profit, praiſe, and authority. Nor is it to be doubted, but that greater miſchiefes and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences
<pb facs="tcp:2838:81"/>
may enſue, if they ſhall ſuffer theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cords, and raging warres, to abide in their ſtrength but little longer. For it is not probable, that thoſe princes who have bin diſveſted of their eſtates, dri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven into exile, and brought to the point of diſpaire, will ever be quiet, as long as they can expect any reliefe, or helpe elſewhere; nay, they will leave no ſtone unmoved, no meanes unaſſayed, but as it is in the proverbe, will move both Heaven and Hell; and to conclude, like the Serpents, whoſe head being bruiſed, doe laſt of all threaten with their taile; will leave no thing unattempted, wherby they may be inabled to returne into their Countrey, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their loſt eſtates. And this certainely will bring with it moſt ſtrange, and dangerous changes of ſtate, miniſter fuell to a perpetuall warre, tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and terrifie the Princes of the Empire with continuall feare, and at laſt, haſten the utter ruine, and deſtruction of the Commonweale.</p>
            <p>Beſides, the forraigners, which either would abate the puiſſance, and authority of the Caeſarean Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the houſe of Auſtria, the foundations whereof are thought to be laid in Germany, ſeeke for profit in the rubbiſh of the Empire, or revenge private injuries, or endeavour a change of govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, may alwayes have an occaſion to purſue their deſigne, whileſt under the ſhew of helpe, to which they will profeſſe themſelves bound, for the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of their baniſhed friends, and allies, they may diſpatch their owne intendments. It is to be feared alſo, leaſt the Turkes uſing, and being moved with
<pb facs="tcp:2838:81"/>
this occaſion, riſe up, and with their whole power before they have any loſſe, invade Germany alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſhaken and much weakned, to the conqueſt whereof they have long time applied themſelves, and yet attend the opportunity of the ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>All theſe, and other innumerable miſchiefes might have long ſince been prevented, if all private quarrels, enmities, and factions ſet apart; the peace, and concord, and ancient conſent, and harmonie of affections had bin reduced, and eſtabliſhed amongſt the Princes, and by a common, and publike accord, care had been taken, and proviſion made, for the ſafetie, and ſecuritie of the Common-weale. And this ſurely had beene eaſily done, if thoſe counſels, and remedies which availed to that purpoſe, and were in a readineſſe, had been ſooner taken, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied; of which, theſe two alone are thought the moſt convenient, and efficacious. Firſt, if a generall, and univerſall amneſtie of things paſt had been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creed; ſecondly every one, (no man excluded out of this peace, and amneſtie) who by warre, and the injury of times, was caſt downe from his fortunes, and honours, had bin intirely reſtored to the eſtate, which he poſſeſſed before theſe ſtirres began. For this is moſt certaine; that there can bee no firme ground found out for a concord in Germany; that no peace, no leagues will endure long, which are not concluded with the conſent, and will of all who are intereſſed therein, and with reſtitution and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction to the baniſhed perſons. The other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, if any be remaining to be agreed upon, and
<pb facs="tcp:2838:82"/>
added would have paſſed without difficulty, or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ception. For, out of doubt, the ſtrangers, who have engaged themſelves in this warre; by this meanes, all pretence of the continuation thereof being taken from them, would willingly have refrained Armes, and entertained peace.</p>
            <p>Againe, by reſtitution of the Palatinate, <hi>Charles Lodowicke</hi> the Electour being received into his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer degree, and dignitie; the Emperour and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours might have gained this advantage, that they might have layd a farre ſtronger, ſurer, and ſetled foundation of an univerſall peace, than by the trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of Prague; all hope being taken from their ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of invading, and oppreſſing the Germane Common-wealth, and the other provinces (yet free) from the tyrannie of warre. And withall as they might have purchaſed a moſt glorious and happy peace, and ſecurity for the Roman-Germane Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire, themſelves, their friends, allies, and people: ſo to conclude, might they have delivered the youth of Germany (by ſo many ſlaughters and miſeries, redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced from ſo great a number, to ſuch an admired, and unheard of ſcarſitie) from famine, mourning, ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, and griefe, by which as by a gentle fire they were daily waſted, and deſtroyed. Beſides, it had beene no ſmall honour to the Emperour and Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours, if they had replaced, and ſetled in their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient honours and poſſeſſions, the Princes Palatine, deſcended of ſuch a Princely Race, joyned in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanguinitie with the principall families of the Kings and Princes of Europe, whoſe progenitours have
<pb facs="tcp:2838:82"/>
ſo well deſerved of the Empire, (for the greatneſſe, glory, liberty, and ſafety whereof, they have beene ever moſt carefull conſtant defenders and abetters) for whom alſo ſo many Kings, and Princes, whom the reſtitution did concerne, had interceded and briefly, who might bee, an ornament and profit to the Empire.</p>
            <p>By this action, they ſhould not onely have firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obliged the Palatines to them; and have found them ready and gratefull, in the returning of all lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving offices, and good affection; but, alſo prevailed with the moſt illuſtrious King of Great Britaine, that in teſtimony of his gratefull minde, out of his ſingular good affection to the Germane Common-weale, he would have conſented, to have entred into covenants with his Imperiall Majeſtie, and the Princes of the Empire, as well for the ſettling of a generall peace (the groundworke thereof being firſt laid upon the reſtitution of the Palatinate) as for the maintaining thereof, againſt all that durſt oppoſe it. How great an advantage, ſecurity, and glory might have accrewed to the Empire by the alliance, and defenſive Armes of this moſt puiſſant King, the Emperour and the Electours might eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly judge, if they would have taken into their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration the condition of their owne eſtates, the preſent times and calamities of the Countrey of Germany brought to the neereſt ſtep of ruine.</p>
            <p>All this then being truth, you ſhall give me leave O yee men, Princes, Peeres, and free Denizons, that my ſpeech may turne to you, before I come to
<pb facs="tcp:2838:83"/>
a concluſion. I Intreat and beſeech you, by the everliving God, by all things divine and humane, by the Aſhes of your Anceſtours, by the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Countrey, to conſider in what eſtate your af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires have been, and in what they now are, what miſeries you have ſuffered already, and what doe yet ſurround, and hang over you, if you ſhall yet neglect to adviſe ſpeedily for your owne ſafety <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd eſtates. Obſerve you not that by the fortune of ſtrangers affecting ſoveraigntie, by their counſels, and ſupplies of money, the liberty, authority, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune, dignity, and glory are ſo ſhaken by theſe ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill warres, that it is in all probabilitie to be feared, leaſt your ſelves being brought to povertie, and ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very, ſhall be forced to live under a perpetual yoke. Whom can you blame for this, but your ſelves? If preſently upon the beginning ye had ſeriouſly un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaken the cauſe of <hi>Fredericke</hi> (through whoſe ſides ye were ſtricken) either to defend it, or to compound it: If with joynt courage, force, and counſell, you had oppoſed your ſelves to this co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetous deſire of ſoveraigntie, and the diligence uſed for the ſpoile of your liberty and religion, when it was in the birth or moving from the cradle; things had gone farre better with you, and you ſhould have gained a good report, for valour, conſtancy, and piety; in place of the ignominy, blame cowar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dice and miſery, which doe now attend you. But, with extreame ſhame, and diſhonour, not without ſuſpicion of betraying and forſaking your friends, you have ſuffered one, to be loſt, and devoured af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb facs="tcp:2838:83"/>
another, thinking that their caſe did not at all concerne you. What? know you not that alwayes they whom cowardice and wicked ſubtiltie hath detained from Armes, to the end they might bee ſecured by other mens perils have ſuffered moſt ſeverely? <hi>Rex Mithridates ad Regem Anſacem apud Saluſtium, lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Hiſt.</hi> you could have done no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that could be more gratefull to your ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, by nothing have they had greater advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage againſt you, then that you did not conſult in common, that you did not joyne your forces, and Armes; and with one conſent oppoſe this danger, which hung over all promiſcuouſly; ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, while each of you have fought ſingly, you have been overcome generally. <hi>Ex Tacito in vita Agricolae.</hi> Againe, either willingly you would, or have ſuffered your ſelves to be deluded, and ſedu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced with promiſes, and gifts; to be disjoyned, and ſevered each from other, to bee deceived, and corrupted with a falſe gloſſe of friendſhip or fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour. Have you not obſerved, that it is cuſtoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry with them which take up Armes with a deſire of Soveraigntie, for the ſetling of their owne au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, and the ſubverſion of religion and liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, to give out, that they intend no offenſive warre againſt all in generall, but againſt ſome in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, untill thoſe being vanquiſhed, whom firſt they fell upon, they may proceede by degrees againſt ſome others, and in the end againſt all. <hi>Iacobus Zevecotius in obſervatis politicis ad Suetonii
<pb facs="tcp:2838:84"/>
Tranquilli Iulium Caeſarem, cap.</hi> 35. Thus you have been deceived, and deluded with the falſe colours of their good affection, and grace, who have made warre for your deſtruction, and the ingroſſing of your wealth (the onely end by them at firſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded) which have fallen upon you ſingly, whileſt you not thinking that you were the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons aimed at, have beene wanting both to your ſelves, and your Neighbours, ingaging them in a dangerous warre, and haſtening your owne ruine. Fina ly, there have happened diſcords, ſchiſmes, diſſenſion, diviſion of counſels, hatred, both pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like and private, cauſed, raiſed, and increaſed by difference of religion, and ſubtill ſuggeſtions of calumniators, envies, emulations, pride, preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, falſe conceits, of your owne power, hope vainely placed, and ungrounded; of forraigne ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plies, diſtruſt, and malicious crafts in forbearing to ſuccour your friends, unthankfulneſſe, brea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king and voiding leagues, and covenants; and many other things of that nature, which were then, and are yet practiſed amongſt you, and theſe reduced the Germane Commonweale (once the moſt flouriſhing ſtate of the world) to mourning, deſolation and extreame miſery. And now (but too late) you finde and apprehend what manner of troubles ſurround you, with what chaines and fetters you are manacled, in what a Labyrinth, and priſon you are incloſed. Could you be igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, that they, who intended to lay a yoake of
<pb facs="tcp:2838:84"/>
ſlavery upon a free Nation, caſt out many falſe miſts, and ſeeme rather to doe any thing, but what they doe, and ſo long pretend the preſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of liberty, and the obſervation of ancient cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtomes, till they have taken away all hope of their recovery, and abundantly aſſured themſelves of the meanes to ſoveraignty? <hi>Iacobus Zevecotius in obſervatis politicis ad Suetonii Tranquilli Iulium Cae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſarem, ut ſupra citavimus. cap.</hi> 79 <hi>in ſine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Pardon me, I beſeech you, you men, and Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, if you thinke I have ſpoken too freely, and boldly; Know, that I am alſo a Germane, and care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full of the Germane credit, honour, eſtimation, and libertie, that I am moved with the calamities of our countrey, and racked betwixt anger and ſorrow becauſe I ſee both it and you to periſh ſo miſerably; and ſo ſoone, and ſo diſhonourably to loſe all the repute, credite, dignitie, libertie, the Empire deſcended from our Anceſtours, and their gotten glories, and become a prey, ſcorne, and contempt to ſtrangers. To ſpeake with the Oratour, Wee paſſe no day without teares, nor ever leave to bewaile our Countrey, and lament this alteration.</p>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. <bibl>Iſocr.</bibl>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Theſe, theſe, are the cauſes of Our great ſorrowes.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
